<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a person of quality, occasioned by a printed libel, entituled, The cause of the difference between Tobias Cage esquire, and Mary his wife stated by the said Mary in a letter to a gentleman, for her own vindication: the design, malice, and falshood whereof is hereby detected with proofs by persons of value, on oath, and otherwise.</title>
            <author>Cage, Tobias.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1692B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222690</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833833</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833833</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38311</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70441)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38311)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2212:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a person of quality, occasioned by a printed libel, entituled, The cause of the difference between Tobias Cage esquire, and Mary his wife stated by the said Mary in a letter to a gentleman, for her own vindication: the design, malice, and falshood whereof is hereby detected with proofs by persons of value, on oath, and otherwise.</title>
                  <author>Cage, Tobias.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. [28]: T.C. i.e. Tobias Cage.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Copy trimmed with loss of pagination and text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cage, Mary. --  Cause of the difference between Tobias Cage esquire, and Mary his wife --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> to a Perſon of Quality, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a printed Libel, Entituled, <hi>The Cauſe of the Difference between</hi> Tobias Cage <hi>Eſquire, and</hi> Mary <hi>his Wife:</hi> Stated by the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> in a Letter to a Gentleman, for her own Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The Deſign, Malice, and Falſhood whereof is hereby detected with Proofs by Perſons of value, on Oath, and otherwiſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Cannot but acknowledge my obligation to you for acquainting me with this Libel, which is as falſe as Hell it ſelf: The deſign of it was to obſtruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my being diſcharged of my Bonds, for the Peace which my Wife maliciouſly bound me in; whereby ſhe conceives her Friend (as ſhe calls him in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Libel) would be preſerved in his Perſon, and the Jury who is to try the Cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> between her Husband and that Friend, be poſſeſſed with ſome obliquities in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Husband, and ſo award the leſs for damages; but principally in purſuance of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> old wicked Deſign between her and her Friend for a ſeparation from her Husband believing that a Gentleman can never poſſibly digeſt ſuch Slanders and Indignitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from a Wife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> We are not to judge either of the Integrity, or Wickedneſs of a Man by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Affliction, or Proſperity in this Life; <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>the ſame event hapneth to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Juſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt;</hi> nor yet by what is ſaid on the one ſide or the other, <hi>but from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mouth of two or three Witneſſes.</hi> You know <hi>Job</hi> was ſaid to be wicked, becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he was afflicted. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſaid to be a peſtilent Fellow, and mad when he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Bonds; and <hi>Sir,</hi> you know who was accuſed to be a Wine-bibber, and a Frien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Publicans and Sinners: <hi>Job</hi> alſo had his Wife, and <hi>David</hi> his <hi>Michal;</hi> and yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know that Law among the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians, That every man ſhould bear rule in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own Houſe,</hi> was publiſh'd upon <hi>Vaſhties</hi> contempt of her Husband. Even <hi>Socrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the patient Philoſopher had his <hi>Xantippe,</hi> aſwell as others. <hi>Sir,</hi> It hath pleaſe God to exerciſe me with Afflictions moſt of my days, yet hath his Providenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miraculouſly ſupported me, and that under this trial by ſuch a Wife as <hi>Solomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> reckons, <hi>a continual dropping, and as rottenneſs in the Bones.</hi> I am not ignorant o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the nature and duties of a married Life, and have now twice experienced it. I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found (as <hi>Charon</hi> of Wiſdom calls it) the firſt a Paradiſe, and this laſt a Hell i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> compariſon of that ſweet ſociety of Life I enjoyed for ſixteen Years with my forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wife, of whom I ever did and muſt ſay with an honour to her Memory, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou excelled'ſt them all:</hi> but what I can ſay of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that truly, I ſhall forbear in all things not neceſſary for my defence.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                  <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I ſhall anſwer that infamous Libel with all the moderation I can, and only ſhew in a plain, familiar, and hiſtorical way the whole truth and occaſion of the unparallell'd differences between me and my Wife, or rather (as ſhe calls it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and me: ſome of the Paragraphs of the Libel I recite, and anſwer parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly; others as ſummarily as I can, to avoid prolixity, and make all good with Proofs.</p>
            <p>Libel 1. <hi>It being my own intereſt as well as my obligation to ſatisfie you in your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, I ſhall give you a faithful and impartial account of the riſe and continuance of the difference between me and my Husband.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This <hi>Sir,</hi> deſerves a Remarque; The Perſon that thus invites a Wife to condemn her Husband he never heard, and that in Print, merits a character that he may be known by; he has taken the deſigns of his counſels from <hi>Achitophel.</hi> When <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abſalom</hi> his ſon were at difference, <hi>Achitophel</hi> counſelled him to go in unto his Fathers Concubines, in the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that all <hi>Iſrael</hi> might know he was abhorred of his Father; adding, that then his hands ſhould be ſtrengthened. Such is this counſel, and given with the ſame expectation; and becauſe this Anarchical Counſellor is nameleſs, I will call him <hi>Achitophel,</hi> who when he reflects upon his own iniquity in this matter, eſpecially if the hoped for effects of his counſels fail, perhaps may ſet his Houſe in order, and make the ſame good end.</p>
            <p>Libel 2. <hi>Before my intermarriage with Mr.</hi> Cage, <hi>I did by the name of</hi> Mary Okey <hi>ſecure all my Eſtate in the hands of Mr.</hi> John Okey <hi>as my Truſtee, for the ſeparate main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of my ſelf,</hi> Elizabeth Blackwel, <hi>and</hi> Mary Okey, <hi>my two Daughters by my two former Husbands; and that by a Deed drawn by Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>himſelf: ſo that no ſurpriſe in the caſe could be pretended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note, That here ſhe ſaith, <hi>She made proviſion for the maintenance of her ſelf and her Children:</hi> and <hi>pag.</hi> 7. that had ſhe known ſuch a condition had been foiſted into her Articles, <hi>viz. of maintaining her ſelf and her Children,</hi> ſhe would never have been the Wife of Mr. <hi>Cage.</hi> Here obſerve her juſtice and affection, and how <hi>Achitophels</hi> cunning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ailed in ſuffering her thus to contradict her ſelf: but <hi>ſome ſort of People have had memories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. This cannot be anſwered but by giving account of the whole tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction before the Marriage, and the ſeveral times of every action; and therefore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the beginning of the Year 1669, I buried my former Wife, with whom my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow Wife was well acquainted and familiar 14 Years before, and had been ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al times at my Houſe with her. And about the latter end of <hi>October,</hi> the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear I and my preſent Wife met at Mr. <hi>Doelittles,</hi> where ſhe took notice of my Wives death; and ſhortly after came to adviſe with me as Counſel in her ſuite, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etween her ſelf and Mr. <hi>John Aſhburnham,</hi> and deſired one of my Clerks might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake care of it, which gave frequent opportunities of converſe. Within a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime ſhe deſired me to diſpoſe of 500 <hi>l.</hi> for her at Intereſt, thereupon ſent me the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00 <hi>l.</hi> by Mr. <hi>Okeys</hi> Son, without taking any Note for the ſame; <hi>which pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſerve.</hi> This I put out to Mr. <hi>Neal,</hi> in the names of Dr. <hi>Paget,</hi> and <hi>John Okey,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the latter end of <hi>November</hi> of the ſame Year: at which time I had no reſolution <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrying with her. But ſhe having carried her ſelf very obliging to me. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:2"/> Friends ſuſpecting ſome affection in the caſe, endeavoured to divert me; ſome giving one reaſon, ſome another, and propoſing conſiderable Matches; but I do acknowledge that her extraordinary carriage towards me, made me believe there was affection, and that ſhe would make me a very tender and loving Wife, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering the circumſtances ſhe was under, of two young Children; and the diſcouragement and manner of her Husband <hi>Okeys</hi> death, which was then uſed as an argument againſt my marrying her. I then deſired them to forbear, and declar'd that as the truth was, I had never propos'd or mention'd marriage to her, but if I knew that ſhe had a real affection for me, I would marry her. At this time I knew not ſhe was worth a Groat more than the five hundred Pounds I had put out, unleſs the 250 <hi>l.</hi> in Suite with Mr. <hi>Aſhburnham,</hi> prov'd good, which appear'd then deſperate.</p>
            <p>The truth of this Mr. <hi>Thomas Dun</hi> of <hi>Spittlefields,</hi> or Mris. <hi>Rebecka Fowk</hi> at Mr. <hi>Buchanons</hi> Houſe in <hi>Chancery-Lane</hi> knows, who were the Perſons preſent at this Diſcourſe. Notwithſtanding this reſolution, I ſuffered her to go out of Town, I never ſpake any thing to her of my thoughts of marrying her, until ſhe return'd to her Couſen <hi>Okeys</hi> in <hi>Lawrence Lane,</hi> and had layen ſick a Week there, and ſent for me, nor until ten days before we married.</p>
            <p>Before the 15th of <hi>December,</hi> we agreed to marry on the 21th following, the Marriage-Clothes were making before any diſcourſe touching Eſtate on either ſide. But I being willing to free my ſelf from the uncertain expectations of her Children, by ſeeing ſome proviſion made for them before I married, I deſired to know what her Eſtate was, and what ſhare thereof her Children ſhould have: She told me that her Eſtate in all was 1500 <hi>l.</hi> good and bad Debts, and Jewels; and ſhewed me her Jewels, and preſented them to me, as ſhe hath confeſſed upon her Oath, by anſwer to the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Bill, to make me pay the value thereof, although ſhe knows Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> the Goldſmith new ſet them faſhionable at my charge, which coſt me 12 <hi>l.</hi> and I return'd them to her again, and never had any of them ſince in my cuſtody or power, but a <hi>Saphire</hi> Stone of thirty Shillings. I deſir'd a particular of the Eſtate: ſhe refer'd me to Mr. <hi>Okey,</hi> who gave me a particular in Writing, as follows, Mr. <hi>Neal</hi> 500 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ballard,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> 500 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Garth</hi> 100 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Aſhburnham</hi> 250 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Roſe</hi> 40 <hi>l.</hi> Jewels 100 <hi>l. Ephraim Manſil</hi> 40 <hi>l.</hi> In all 1500 and odd Pounds. This I acquainted her with, and deſired her to make ſome ſettlement, which ſhe refuſed, but left the whole to me, to propoſe, order, diſpoſe, and ſettle as I thought fit. But at my importunity, ſhe declared at firſt that her Daughters ſhould have 200 <hi>l.</hi> a piece; then at my further requeſt, that her Daughter <hi>Mary Okey</hi> ſhould have 400 <hi>l.</hi> and her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> not ſo much: Thereupon I preſſed her to name ſome Counſel, to conſult with me about a ſettlement of the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> which ſhe refuſed alſo, but left the matter wholly to me, whether I would ſettle it or no. Then I deſired to know whether ſhe was any way indebted, or was likely to have any other Suite or trouble, but that with <hi>Aſhburnham;</hi> to which ſhe and Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> anſwered, ſhe had not; and thereupon I drew the Deed of Settlement in the beſt manner I could: And becauſe I did not know, nor then enquire, by what kind of Security the ſaid 1500 <hi>l.</hi> was ſecured, whether by Mortgages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Statues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:3"/> Eſtate or Monies which might be gotten in by Suites: but ſhe denying that ſhe was ever likely to have any other Suites; I put as general words in the Deed as I could make uſe of, that I might be ſure to paſs all the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> ſent the draught of the Deed to her by Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> to adviſe with Counſel, which ſhe refuſed to do; but ſhe and <hi>Okey</hi> peruſed the ſame, and the ſame was ſent back to be ingroſſed, which was faithfully ingroſſed accordingly, and by me and her ſigned and ſealed on the Marriage day.</p>
            <p>This Deed was made thus voluntarily by me, not at her requeſt, but to protect and ſecure the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> from any accident by me, and notwithſtanding that Deed, Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> was not to intermeddle with the Eſtate unleſs ſome danger appear'd; and the better to ſecure it I gave ſufficient ſecurity to enable her to reimburſe her ſelf, if it any way hapned to ſuffer by me. <hi>Sir,</hi> For five Years, and until theſe differences were compleated by him ſhe calls Friend, <hi>Okey</hi> the Truſtee, never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedled with the Eſtate, nor to defend Suites touching the Eſtate, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Wife or education of the Children, but all was caſt upon me, as the manager of the Eſtate; and the truth is, I put a greater power and confidence in my Wife and <hi>Okey</hi> than this, relating to her ſecurity, which ſhe hath perfideouſly broken.</p>
            <p>The truth of all which Allegations is proved by depoſitions of Witneſſes exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and that the Deed was ingroſſed according to the original draught thereof.</p>
            <p>Note, That the true Marriage-agreement lying only in the knowledge of Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> the Truſteé, the Court of Chancery (after the differences came there) ordered him to be examined as a Witneſs, which my Wife would not ſuffer until he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon Contempt; and then he and his Wife ſubmitted to be examined: and his Depoſition does agree in all the particulars with his Anſwer to my Bill in <hi>Chancery</hi> againſt him, all which and all other proof under the hand of the Court ſhall at any time be ſent to Mr. <hi>Miles,</hi> Scrivener in <hi>Threed-Needle-ſtreet,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Crown Tavern,</hi> to be peruſed by any Perſon that deſires ſatisfaction in the ſame, upon notice there left.</p>
            <p>That part of Mr. <hi>Okeys</hi> teſtimony which relates to this matter before ſet forth, I have here inſerted immediately after this, and the reſt of the Proofs are at the end of this Letter all together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Okey</hi> being ſworn and examined, depoſeth, that when the Marriage was in agitation, the particular of Mrs. <hi>Cages</hi> Eſtate given in was 1500 <hi>l.</hi> which conſiſted in theſe, Mr. <hi>Neal</hi> 500 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> 300 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ballard</hi> 100 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Aſhburnham</hi> 250 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Garth</hi> 100 <hi>l.</hi> This Deponent 100 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Roſe</hi> 40 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ephraim Manſel</hi> 40 <hi>l.</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Maries</hi> Jewels 100 <hi>l.</hi> and this Deponent knows, that the ſaid <hi>Mary</hi> did leave the matter touching the Eſtate wholly to Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> to propoſe, order, and ſettle as he thought fit; and knows, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did voluntarily declare, that he was reſolved to ſettle the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> in the Mothers power for the maintenance of her and her Children, and ſuch Children as he ſhould have by her; and did ſeal and deliver the Deed accordingly, that he managed Mrs. <hi>Cages</hi> Eſtate ſeveral Years before the Marriage, but he did not know that ſhe was indebted, had any other Eſtate, or was lyable to any Suites or troubles. And that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>luntarily, and of his own accord and free will, draw and ſeal the ſaid Deed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:3"/> Perſon for her; and that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> made the Deed purely upon the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that her Portion was 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and in order to preſerve the ſame for the maintenance of the ſaid Defendant <hi>Mary</hi> in cohabitation with her Husband, and for the maintenance, education, and preferment of her Children ſhe had and might have by him. That Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> did acquaint the Deponent, that ſhe had known Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> in his former Wifes days ſeveral Years, and when he was in his troubles, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> gave ſecurity to enable her to reimburſe her ſelf, in caſe the Eſtate ſhould ſuffer by his means. That he doth not know when he was to enter on that truſt; he did not, nor was he deſired for five Years after the Marriage, nor until Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> and her Husband differed, and during that five Years Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> without any controul, managed all the Eſtate, maintained the Wife, and educated the Children with Muſick, Dancing, and other Accompliſhments, ſo as Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was very well pleaſed therewith, and kept a Houſe and Servants for them and their accommodation at <hi>Highgate.</hi> This is the ſubſtance of what is ſworn, both by his Depoſitions and Anſwers, as to this matter. Mrs. <hi>Okey</hi> the Truſtees Wife in many things ſweareth the ſame with her Husband, and that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was very deſirous of the Marriage, and did declare to Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> (before the Marriage) that ſhe was no way indebted, nor likely to have any Suites but Mr. <hi>Aſhburnhams,</hi> nor did ſhe ever hear her ſay ſhe had any Eſtate but 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and againſt the Marriage ſhe ſold ſome Goods to make that up.</p>
            <p>Libel 3. <hi>Notwithſtanding this ſettlement, my Husband after Marriage got into his Hands a great part of the Eſtate belonging to me and my Daughters, partly by the facility of Mr.</hi> Okey <hi>my Truſtee, who having ſeveral Writings and Buſineſs in the Hands of my Husband, was afraid of offending him; and therefore both paid him Money contrary to my order, and ſuffered him to receive a conſiderable Debt (given by his Royal Highneſs to my Children,) beſides other Money; all which he ſtill keeps to himſelf, and partly by other indirect means, as by getting moſt of my Jewels and Plate from me, under pretence of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing them (whilſt we ſhould be in the Country,) and then converting them to his own uſe, and that I deceived her, pretending to put out Money to one Mr.</hi> Mills.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. The ſettlement was made to ſecure the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> Eſtate, for the maintenance of her and her Children, and ſuch Children as I ſhould have by her, upon confidence that ſhe was no way indebted, nor was any way liable unto, or likely to have any Suites but that of <hi>Aſhburnhams,</hi> which was depending before I married her. I was ſcarce warm in my wedding Sheets before Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> of <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet,</hi> by Mrs. <hi>Walters,</hi> (ſince Mrs. <hi>Vinor,</hi>) demands of me 300 <hi>l.</hi> due by Bond from my Wife. Mr. <hi>Kirkham</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet</hi> demanded 30 <hi>l.</hi> expended by him for her uſe. One <hi>Ryſe Yates</hi> to whom there was a 100 <hi>l.</hi> due by Bond from Collonel <hi>Okey,</hi> which ſhe had promiſed to pay him for ſervice in the management of her affairs for ſeveral years. One <hi>Valentine</hi> demanded of me 10 <hi>l.</hi> due by Note for nurſing of her Daughter Miſs <hi>Okey.</hi> One Mrs. <hi>Pool</hi> demanded of me about 4 or 6 <hi>l.</hi> for Silver Lace bought of her. Mr. <hi>Tottenham</hi> a <hi>Linnen-Draper</hi> demanded about the ſame Sum for Linnen. Mr. <hi>Somes</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard demanded about 8 <hi>l.</hi> (as I remember) for Woolen Cloth. And Mr. <hi>John Blackwel</hi> her firſt Husbands Son hath ſince demanded near 300 <hi>l.</hi> for Goods and Jewels, proved to to be delivered to her at a price agreed on; and threatned to ſue me upon a Bond of 5000 <hi>l.</hi> ſhe entred into to him before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:4"/> to claim any thing of his but what he gave her by his Will. To ſtay which Suite, I obtain'd an Injunction in <hi>Chancery.</hi> Several other Debts were demanded of me, and I ſued for ſeveral of them; and by this judge what a dear, a faithful Wife ſhe was like to prove to me, who brought me her ſelf and two Children to maintain and educate. An Eſtate rackt up at her own value at 1500 <hi>l.</hi> whereof there was not 1100 <hi>l.</hi> ſecure; had I not reaſon then to get into my hands what Eſtate I could of hers to defend my ſelf, and to take theſe concealments of her Debts very unkindly? But I did neither, for I did never receive of her Truſtee <hi>Okey</hi> of her Money, more than 20 <hi>l.</hi> which was paid towards the purchaſe of the Houſe at <hi>Highgate.</hi> True it is, I did Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> ſome ſervice, but I do not know that I ever had any Writings of value of his in my Hands for three days together, and when ſhe clamour'd at him for imploying me, I voluntarily left his buſineſs. For the Plate and Jewels ſhe pretends to, I do affirm ſhe had no other pieces of Plate, than a Silver Thimble, Bodkin, and Spoon; therefore I could get none of them into my Hands. For her Jewels, ſhe had no Neck-lace but a black Bobbin and one of Glaſs. She had indeed a Phoenix Jewel, and ſome old Rings, which ſhe afterward valued at a 100 <hi>l.</hi> (not worth 50 <hi>l.</hi>) part of the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> which Ring and the <hi>Phoenix</hi> ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me as an <hi>Emblem</hi> of her ſelf the fourth day I had declared my intention of marrying her. True it is, the 21th of <hi>December</hi> I unhappily married her; after which, being a thing ſo ſuddenly done, and not accommodated with a Houſe, I brought her to my Chamber at <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> which is none of the worſt Chambers: She thinking that too mean for her, complained ſhe was never ſo lodged in her life. Then I removed to Lodgings in a great Houſe in <hi>Fullers</hi> Rents; there ſhe carried her ſelf ſo imperiouſly, that the Miſtriſs of the Houſe was weary of her; and I being deſirous that ſhe might be pleaſed, deſired her to chuſe where ſhe would be, ſhe choſe one Mrs. <hi>Shermans</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire,</hi> which though it was inconvenient for me, I agreed to it; and in <hi>March</hi> after our Marriage, waited upon her thither, where there was one Mrs. <hi>Sparks,</hi> a Widow Gentlewoman, and an acquaintance of hers, Daughter to Mrs. <hi>Sherman,</hi> who ſince married one Mr. <hi>Minors</hi> of <hi>Lichfield;</hi> there in a little time, ſhe ſo deported her ſelf, and abuſed Mrs. <hi>Minors,</hi> that Mrs. <hi>Sherman</hi> was weary of her company. Then we returned to the Houſe in <hi>Fullers</hi> Rents again, where in a little time ſhe ſhewed her ſelf of the ſame temper; and thereupon I conceiving that none of thoſe Perſons where ſhe had lived had been educated fit for a Companion for her, I found out a place in <hi>Grays-Inn-Lane,</hi> where one Madam <hi>Burcher,</hi> who had been the Widow of Mr. <hi>Thomas,</hi> a Gentleman in <hi>Kent</hi> did lodge and table Perſons of Quality, and there I carried her, her Daughter <hi>Okey</hi> and her Maid; and ſhortly after, her other Daughter and Siſter came to me, for whom I paid the ſame proportion, for whom and my ſelf I paid 4 <hi>l:</hi> a Week. In a ſhort time ſhe deported her ſelf ſo haughtily, unquiet, and diſobligingly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Mrs. <hi>Burcher,</hi> that I was forced to think of ſome new place, hoping that ſhe would be more quiet in a Houſe where ſhe might have none to contend with. I gave her her choice of Houſes neer <hi>London,</hi> ſhe reſolved upon Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> Houſe at <hi>Highgate,</hi> which ſhe had ſeen when ſhe lived with the Lady Marchioneſs of <hi>Dorcheſter:</hi> Of this Houſe at firſt, I could have but part, which I took, carried her thither, took Servants for her, and ſupplied her with all things neceſſary: In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38311:4"/> Houſe; and in regard Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> had but a Term of Years, ſhe deſired me to treat with Mr. <hi>Blake</hi> who had the reverſion, who was unwilling to ſell it; and therefore I agreed with Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> for his Term, which was eleven Years, for which ſhe promiſed to lay out part of her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> died before Writings were ſealed, the Houſe was out of repair, the Gardens ruined, the Fences all down; yet I agreed with Mr. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Archers</hi> Aſſignee, for a 100 <hi>l.</hi> of which having no Witneſs, Mr. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> preſently ſold it to a Neighbour for a 120 <hi>l.</hi> which my Wife took for ſuch an affront, that ſhe put me upon ſuing for my Bargain in <hi>Chancery,</hi> which I accordingly did, ſued for the ſame in my own and Wifes name, to be ſettled upon her; which Suite was ſoon determined, a Conveyance drawn and engroſſed, of the Houſe to her Truſtee <hi>Okey,</hi> with an Indorſement thereon, under my Hand and Seal, that the Money paid for it was part of her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> that the Conveyance was made in truſt for her, and to be diſpoſed of by her according to Marriage-ſettlement; which Deed with the Indorſement was and is left with Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> the Truſtee, and the ſame is proved by the Depoſition of Mr. <hi>Anthony Smith</hi> in <hi>Chancery,</hi> who ingroſſed the Bill in <hi>Chancery,</hi> Deed, and Indorſement: judge therefore how true that charge of the Libel is, that I made the Conveyance of the Houſe to my own uſe.</p>
            <p>And as to that of Mr. <hi>Mills,</hi> there is ſomething of truth in that, but not as the Libel declares. The <hi>Michaelmas</hi> after my unhappy Marriage, I received of Mr. <hi>Neal</hi> 25 <hi>l.</hi> for 500 <hi>l.</hi> of her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> I had laid out with him for 100 <hi>l. p. an.</hi> for ſeven Years by her conſent; 25 <hi>l.</hi> whereof I did put out to Mr. <hi>Mills,</hi> and in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term (her Cauſe with Mr. <hi>Aſhburham</hi> being to be heard in <hi>Chancery</hi>) I did take that 25 <hi>l.</hi> in to imploy the ſame in defence of Mr. <hi>Aſhburhams</hi> Suite, but as to all other the circumſtances of that allegation, the ſame is abominably falſe throughout. And as to that part which ſays Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> permitted me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a conſiderable Debt, which was granted to her by his Royal Highneſs, is utterly falſe, for the Debt ſhe means, was a Debt due by Bond to Collonel <hi>Okey,</hi> from one <hi>Shepherd,</hi> and one <hi>Rogers,</hi> the remainder of ſome purchaſe Money of a publick Title. The Bond ſhe had in her cuſtody, which ſhe had ſued before my Marriage, and was nonſuited, which the Defendents have alſo ſworn. Two Years after I married her ſhe brought me that Bond, and told me ſhe had ſued it, but could get nothing, and if I could get any thing ſhe would be glad: Thereupon I by agreement with the Dukes Attorney Sir <hi>Francis Goodrike,</hi> ſued the Obligors who lived in <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> by Engliſh Bill in the <hi>Exchequer.</hi> The Perſons being ſo remote, and I having no acquaintance near them, was forced to employ an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney at 50 Miles from them, and Commiſſioners (Strangers to me) at as great a diſtance to examine Witneſſes in the Cauſe. The Sheriff alſo and his Bailiffs, being remote, wrought upon me; ſo that the expence of that Suite coſt me 105 <hi>l.</hi> I recovered by Decree but 250 <hi>l.</hi> of which Mr. <hi>Doelittle,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> being Miniſters of <hi>London,</hi> applying themſelves to me in behalf of <hi>Shepherd,</hi> affirming him to be an honeſt Man, I remitted 50 <hi>l.</hi> ſo that of that Debt which was no part of her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> nor any part of her Eſtate, being before granted away to another Perſon with whom I have ſince had a conteſt, I never received clear a 100 <hi>l.</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h I had before laid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her importunity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:5"/> hindred her at any time to repair to her Truſtee, or to any Perſon but this Friend, and Dr. <hi>Paget,</hi> after he had given her advice not to return home.</p>
            <p>Libel 4. <hi>Obſerving theſe with other contrivances of my Husband, as his preſſing me to ſell</hi> 700 <hi>l. which I have ſettled upon my two Daughters, telling me that he could obtain a Decree in</hi> Chancery <hi>confirming the ſale, grievouſly abuſing me for my denial of it, which was one of the reaſons of his quarrelling with me; and when in this he could not have his ends, to perfect my unhappineſs, his endeavouring to alienate from me the affections of my Children, knowing that all the comfort I have left in this World, is their tenderneſs of me, obedience and dutifulneſs towards me, and particularly in tempting my Daughter</hi> Blackwel <hi>to go into</hi> France, <hi>for the advantage of her better breeding than</hi> England <hi>could afford her; offering to go with her himſelf to ſettle her there, which he did, that he might upon her account have a ſeeming juſt pretence for his vexatious Suites againſt me, and give ſome ſhew of truth to that falſe and groundleſs Slander in his Anſwer to my Bill, and in his</hi> Affidavit <hi>annexed to his Petition to my Lord Chancellour, where he makes his reproving me for my ſeverity to my Children one cauſe of our difference; when indeed he perfectly hates them for their affection and obedience to me, and becauſe they will not be drawn off from me to him, and fearing that by degrees he would get all my Eſtate into his Hands, and then turn me and my Children out of doors; and alſo, having diſcovered his deſign of quitting me, by a Letter under his own hand, (in anſwer to one writ to him by a Friend of his, adviſing him to deal honeſtly and juſtly with me and my Children,) which Letter was ſhewed and read to me, wherein he declares that it had been, and ſtill was his deſign, which he would purſue, to part with me; and likewiſe, being adviſed by the ſame Friends of his to look to my ſelf, otherwiſe he would not leave me Bread, I endeavoured to hinder his receiving any more Money of mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. I never was guilty of deſigning any wrong or injury to her or her Children; nor did I ever know or hear that ſhe ſettled or deſigned to ſettle 700 <hi>l.</hi> upon her Children; or did I ever move her to ſell or part with any part of her Eſtate, ſaving to her Children; nor did I ever oppoſe her, or differ with her touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Eſtate, or giving her Children any part of it, but the true and only cauſes are as follow. About three Years after my Marriage (the Friend mentioned, and intended in her Letter) repaired often to my Houſe in my abſence, and never but once, and to my Chamber twice or thrice at moſt to my remembrance, in my preſence; and when he had been there, I found her at my return home, always very diſcourſive and talkative, touching Perſons not fit to be his or her Subject of Diſcourſe, now ſhe was my Wife, to ſay no more: All theſe intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences of publick affairs ſhe derived from this pretended Friend, which ſhe did uſually inform me of; and I perceiving them to be dangerous, did admoniſh her to avoid his company. She told him this, and thereupon he ſought occaſions of rendring me in an ill character to my Wife, endeavoured to render me inconſiderable, ſometimes one way, ſometimes another, and uſed this expreſſion, <hi>What did you marry this</hi> Cage <hi>for? I have</hi> 800 <hi>l.</hi> per annum, <hi>and if you had ſtayed, I had married you?</hi> Of this <hi>(Sir)</hi> in diſcontent ſhe one day told me. I then ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting this friend had ſome deſign of making a breach, then begg'd of her to forbear his company: and yet notwithſtanding my requeſt, I had notice that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thither in my abſence ſome conſiderable time after. I having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:5"/> and being informed that ſhe had ſo cruely beaten Miſs <hi>Okey,</hi> for (with that appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation I always treated her Children) I took notice thereof to her, with ſome little earneſtneſs. Shortly after I had complaints of her beating her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> naked in her Bed, with a Hazel Stick, until ſhe brake it, of which her ſaid Daughter keeps a piece to this day, I alſo reproved her for it: After that, finding that ſhe had ſo cruelly abuſed Miſs <hi>Okey,</hi> treading her under her Feet, which did ſo exaſperate the Child, that ſhe got a great piece of Bread and Cheeſe in her Coats and ran away, and reſolved to beg rather than return to her Mother; her Mother ſent about to find her, brought her home, and for her entertainment, beat her until ſhe was all in a gore of Blood; the Child again hid her ſelf, ſometimes in the Hay-Loft, ſometimes under Hedges, nor ever came into the Houſe to eat a bit of Victuals until I returned home, which was three days; when I came home, miſſing the Child, I enquired for her, who at laſt appeared, and her Mother complained of her, I enquiring into the matter, endeavour'd to reconcile them, and when I went to Bed I ſeriouſly diſcourſed my Wife, and adviſed her, and ſhewed her there was no ſuch cauſe of cruelty, and for my pains I was forced to riſe out of Bed at midnight, and walk in the Garden all night. This being <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and on <hi>Monday</hi> morning before I came to Town I reconciled her and her Daughter, as I thought; I was no ſooner gone but ſhe took her Daughter up into the Purple Cloſet, beat her until her Noſe bled, then lock'd her into the Cloſet, until my Wifes Woman taking pity of the Child, look'd in at the Key-hole, ſpied her upon the ground, lying in her Blood, forced open the door and relieved her, who (as the Genlewoman told me) believed ſhe had periſhed had not ſhe relieved her. Another time my Wifes Brother Captain <hi>Roſe</hi> being at <hi>Highgate,</hi> my Wife took a Broom, and with both her hands ſtruck at the head of the Child, which her Brother defended, uſing theſe words to me, Brother, <hi>If you do not interpoſe, my Siſter will ſpoil that Child.</hi> Next ſhe fell upon her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> and beat her moſt cruelly: when I came in I found the Daughter in the Chamber, lamenting her Mothers cruelty; I enquired, and ſhe told me the cauſe which was trivial. I muſt confeſs I was wounded at my very Soul to ſee the daily affliction the poor Children were in under the tyrannical ſpirit of their Mother, ſometimes one, ſometimes the other hiding themſelves for two or three days until I come home, and conceiving that by the marriage of their Mother I was ſomewhat concerned in them, and that it was my duty to interpoſe, I reſolved to do it effectually, and did thorowly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with Arguments from Nature and Scripture, and I think covinced her, but the effect was lamentable: She fell upon me ſaying, <hi>What have you to do with my Children? You, you,</hi> (making hideous grimaces) and pronounced it with ſo il an Accent, that I then thought it was my duty to deal more plainly with her which I did with all the moderation I could. In ſhort, all the return I had from her was, <hi>You are a Rogue, a baſe Fellow,</hi> and ſeveral other opprobrious words. This unexpected language from a Wife, I confeſs made me amazed; but without offering the leaſt violence to her Perſon, I departed to my Chamber at <hi>Grays-Inn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> leaving this reſolution with her, that I would not return again to her until I were juſtified or condemned by ſome of her own Friends or Relations. And this I ker<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> too; and thereupon Collonel <hi>Birch,</hi> Dr. <hi>Paget,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> the Truſtee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:6"/> ſhe was any way faulty, otherwiſe than through diſcontents, (as ſhe pretended) that her Eſtate was waſted, which ſhe had never pretended unto before that inſtant. They refuſed to intermeddle, unleſs I would ſubmit they ſhould enquire into that, and ſettle the matters of Eſtate between us, which I did, ſo that I might be ſecured of quietneſs for the future. At the laſt meeting of theſe Perſons, Collonel <hi>Birch</hi> dictated the heads of an <hi>Award</hi> touching the Eſtate, which though but juſt, was more for my advantage than I expected. The next day Collonel <hi>Birch</hi> informed her of this <hi>Award,</hi> at which ſhe railed at him at Mr. <hi>Okeys</hi> Houſe in ſuch a manner, that from that time he would no more meddle; but at the ſame time a Perſon telling her that I deſired ſhe would return home to me, Dr. <hi>Paget</hi> as I am credibly informed, ſaid no, Let him bite of the Bridle; either he or ſome other preſent ſaid, if he will not ſubmit we will choak him with the Judgement, meaning the ſecurity I had entred into, to ſecure her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> Eſtate after my death, in caſe it ſhould fall ſhort by my means. From this time ſhe abſented her ſelf; and had I not then reaſon to ſuſpect the Doctor, who not only encouraged her in this ſeparation, but went with her to counſel? I confeſs, her ſtubborn abſence greatly afflicted me, nevertheleſs I made all the applications that any Gentleman, nay Man, reaſonably could, by Friends of her own, Miniſters, nay by her own Truſtee, who found her implacable. This being about <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1674, I reſolved as the beſt way to bring her to her ſelf, to ſerve her Truſtee <hi>Okey</hi> with a <hi>Sub-Poena,</hi> to anſwer a Bill in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term following: My intent was, and ſo was the Bill, to complain of her abſence, and to have the Marriage-Deed, or the <hi>Award</hi> of Collonel <hi>Birch,</hi> Dr. <hi>Paget,</hi> and <hi>Okey</hi> decreed. Upon this ſhe complains to Mr. <hi>Abraham Barrington</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> pretending ſhe was willing to do whatſoever he adviſed her, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf to me, and offered his friendly Mediation, which I thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. The further account whereof, and my Grievances then declared, alſo an account of the ſeveral References and Proceedings thereon, and in what manner this pretended Friend hath carried himſelf, you will meet with all by and by.</p>
            <p>As to my deſiring <hi>Betty Blackwel</hi> to go with me into <hi>France;</hi> true it is, I being in this affliction, and ſhe deſperately in love with one Mr. <hi>Browning</hi> a Merchant who failed, and her Mother managing that buſineſs with great indeſcretion and cruelty to her Daughter, and I my ſelf being reſolved to ſtep over into <hi>France</hi> for divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not being able to mind my Imployment, I was willing for <hi>Betty Blackwels</hi> diverſion alſo to carry her over with me, but I do not remember or believe that ever I ſpake or ſent to her of any ſuch thing, nor would I have done it without her Mothers conſent: But I well know Ingratitude is her Mothers nature, and that I am rewarded for my kindneſs to her and hers as her former Husbands for theirs, one of them with treachery, if not both with death: Mr. <hi>Blackwels</hi> Siſter told her ſo before me. And her abuſing Collonel <hi>Okey</hi> in his abſence (ſhe knows how,) and in the Tower her unquietneſs with him, (ſhe knows the circumſtances) denote the kindneſs ſhe had for him; and I ſolemnly proteſt ſhe hath ſaid that her Husband <hi>Blackwel</hi> was an old Knave and deceived her, for that his agreement with the Marqueſs of <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> was to make her a Jointure of ancient Title, and he made it of Fee-Farm-rent, which was loſt by the King's return; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhe importun'd me to inſert in a Bill in <hi>Chancery</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>John Blackwel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38311:6"/> Houſes in <hi>Oldſtreet</hi> which he had ſetled to ſecure her Jointure before the Settlement. That he kept a Whore in his Houſe at <hi>Brogborough</hi> before he married her, but ſhe her ſelf routed her. <hi>Sir,</hi> I find I ſhall be too troubleſom to you to make the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious recitals of the particular Paragraphs of the reſt of the Libel, I will only touch the particular things ſhe charges me withal, and give you ſome Arguments againſt them, where neceſſary and ſufficient Proofs by Depoſitions and living Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies that the Cauſes of Difference are not relating to her Eſtate, or any deſire I ever had to poſſeſs that, but her converſing with this pretended Friend, her cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to her Children, her Unkindneſs, Treachery and Perfideouſneſs to me her Husband, are the Cauſes, and the only Cauſes of my Grief and Trouble.</p>
            <p>And firſt, <hi>Sir,</hi> as to her Falſhood, in pretending that I deſired to ſeparate my ſelf, or break my Marriage-Vows, or that I ever confeſſed to her that I had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Adultery; theſe are the greateſt Wrongs that ever were offered to a Man by a Wife of his boſom: For had this been true that I had acquainted her with ſuch a Folly as a Secret, can you believe any Wife of Generoſity could have diſcovered it? it had been certainly a ſin againſt the moſt common Ingenuity. But I do ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly deny it, or that ever I carnally knew any Woman that was vicious to my knowledge; but for that ſhe her ſelf beſt knows. For my other Wife, I dare anſwer for her, who I am ſure was as vertuous and modeſt as ever was any perſon now a Saint in Heaven. It hath been her practice to aſperſe all of her ſex that have been any way concerned with me (either as Clients, Witneſſes, or Friends) as lewd and vicious, not ſparing my Relations, Perſons of Quality, nor her own Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, her Brother's Daughter; whom I believe was as vertuous (if not more vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) than her own Daughter; I am ſure more juſt, grateful, and modeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I lived forty years before I married this Woman, I was never taxed, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, or gave the leaſt cauſe to ſuſpect I had any converſe with any vicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before I married her. Give me leave to inform you of one Helliſh practice of this Womans, to take off the Teſtimony of one Mrs. <hi>A. Price,</hi> a Miniſters Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that waited on her, a Gentlewoman well known to be vertuous to Mrs. <hi>Pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> the Miniſter's Widow, her Relation is as follows.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> in the time of his Mediation before mentioned, deſired to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſome Servants who had lived with us: this Mrs. <hi>Price</hi> being my Wifes Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, among others was called, and ſpeaking her Conſcience touching my Wifes Behaviour towards my ſelf and her Children; Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> condemned my Wife, and acquainted her, that Mrs. <hi>Price</hi> was a ſober Woman, and being now married had no dependence on us, and that Credit was to be given to her Teſtimony; and ſhe had told him my Wife was very unquiet with me, that I was forced ſometimes to leave my Dinner and Supper, other times to riſe out of my Bed, and walk all Night. Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi>'s Endeavours taking no effect, the Suits at Law proceeded, and this Friend, in the Libel named, reparired with my Wife to Sir <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> Sollicitor General, to retain him. He took their Fee, but with this Condition, That they ſhould refer the Matters in difference to him: to which I alſo ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Sir <hi>Francis</hi> appointed ſeveral days to hear the Matters, we accordingly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. It being demanded of me what my Grievances were, I told him, her keeping this Friend company againſt my injunction the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:7"/> made not many Demands, and applied himſelf to her to ſhew him her Grievaances. Upon which ſhe replied with great art, <hi>Ah Sir!</hi> (with a Sigh fetcht from the Abyſs of Hell) <hi>my Grievances are ſuch as never Womans were; Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>(but I am loth to ſhame him),</hi> and makes a Stop. Pray go on Madam, ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington. I am loth to diſparage Mr.</hi> Cage, ſays ſhe: To which I replied, Wife, we come to deal plainly with Sir <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> he hath been pleaſed to undertake the Cure, he cannot heal unleſs he knows the Wound, and the Bottom of it; therefore pray ſpeak fully the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe went on, <hi>Ah Sir!</hi> (ſighing again) <hi>Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>uſed to riſe from my Bed, and go to bed to my Maid.</hi> How, ſays Sir <hi>Francis Winnington!</hi> I was about to reply, but he ſtopt me, and bid her go on. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>nothing elſe could have made</hi> Mr. Cage <hi>and I at a difference: and Sir, after he had long uſed this, he marries her off; and after he invites her to ſee us at</hi> Highgate, <hi>and when ſhe came, told her his Houſe was at her ſervice, come as often, and ſtay as long as ſhe pleaſed. She muſt ſit at my Table, and if I did not cut her the firſt and beſt piece,</hi> Mr. Cage <hi>was ready to ſtab me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I being not able to hold longer, told Sir <hi>Francis Winington</hi> that I could not have believed there could be ſuch a Deviliſh Deſign hatch'd on this ſide Hell. Upon which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> told her, <hi>I doubt, Madam, you are jealous.</hi> She replies, <hi>Sir, it's paſt that. Madam,</hi> ſaid Sir <hi>Francis, do not conceit ſuch a thing. No, Sir,</hi> (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſhe) <hi>I'le give you Proofs,</hi> and with a brow of Braſs begins thus: <hi>When</hi> Price <hi>was there,</hi> Mr. Cage <hi>forced me to viſit the Lady Marqueſs of</hi> Dorcheſter, <hi>and ſent the Servants and Children, and this Queans Husband to the Garden to Stool-ball, and took his Wife up into my Chamber: I returned home before they expected, and knock'd at the door a good while:</hi> (Sir, I beſeech you obſerve the Cunning and Subtilty of this Woman) <hi>by and by I heard four feet coming down ſtairs, two heavier and two lighter, which I thought had been the Maſtiff-Dogg;</hi> (Note, the Stairs were two Rooms from the Door) <hi>by and by</hi> Mr. Cage <hi>opens the Door, and holds it a-jar, put it to and fro, as if he had been jeſting with me. I obſerved diſorder in his Face as if he had been doing</hi> ſomething, <hi>and with that I thruſt the Door from me, and I ſaw the ſhadow of this Baggage running into the Garden:</hi> To which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> replied, <hi>Madam, Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>and ſhe might be in the Houſe and not naught together; I doubt you are jealous. Nay,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>be gave the Quean twenty ſhillings a time when ſhe lived with me. Ile make it plain to you yet,</hi> (I proteſt I was never ſo amazed in my life, I was wondering what would come next when ſhe thus began again) <hi>I went up into my Chamber, and there my Chamber was diſordered, and my Bed tumbled, I called my Maid</hi> Mary, <hi>and chid her for not ſetting my Chamber in order. She told me that</hi> Mr. Cage <hi>and</hi> Mrs. Price <hi>had been there all the afternoon, and ſhe durſt not come into the Chamber.</hi> Upon which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> took notice, <hi>I pray, Madam, let me ſpeak with that Maid</hi> Mary. She alledged ſhe was gone from her, and could not produce her: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Sir <hi>Francis</hi> adviſed me to find her out, and that ſhe might make Oath touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that matter. The ſaid <hi>Mary,</hi> (who was a Gentleman's Daughter, and waited on my Wife, depoſed, That all this Allegation was untrue, as by her Oath among the Depoſitions hereunto annexed may appear; which when you have read, judge I beſeech you, if ever ſuch a Woman lived before her.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew her further Deceit and Subtilty, obſerve the like about the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:7"/> for a Separation, ſhe pretended great care of me, procured her Siſter to provide a Servant for me to wait on me in my Chamber at <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> for I had none before; ſhe came about <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Tide; my Wife before <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi> abſents: <hi>March</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing 1674 Mr. <hi>Cremor</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> had been informed that this Wench haunted ſuſpected houſes, acquainted me with it, adviſed me to turn her away. I gave her Warning, and in <hi>June</hi> turn'd her away. In <hi>Auguſt</hi> following comes a Letter by the Poſt, directed to Mr. <hi>A. S.</hi> of <hi>Grayes-Inn,</hi> then my Clerk, and is as follows; The Superſcription, <hi>To</hi> Mr. A. S. <hi>at</hi> Mr. Cage's <hi>Chamber in Grays-Inn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the firſt fold opened was wrote, thus, <hi>To Mr.</hi> A. S. <hi>at ſome of the Bawdy-Houſes, or with the Crew in</hi> Grays-Inn. Within thus:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THis is to imform you of the truth. There is one intends to lay the third Child on your back, which I do not really think is yours, but your Maſters; he is better able to keep it, for you have more than you can keep already, for now you begin to want Chink, having no Suppliers but Spenders; you may lick your Breech like a Dog, (if you have any left;) for in ſometime you will not have Money to buy you Plaiſters, and I believe the Squire is in as much need as your ſelf; but he is a Gentleman, therefore I pity him, and if his Wife were dead I would do what I could to help him to ſuch another, but in ſome things ſhe ſhould not be like this, for ſhe ſhould be as ugly as all the Devils could make her, no more wit than himſelf, like an Oſtrich, and as much Heathen as he is Turk. Take this advice young Man, though old in ſin; <hi>Ponder well thy paths, and enter no more into the houſe of an Harlot, leſt thou ſleep the ſleep of death, and ſo be taken in an evil hour.</hi> Thus deſiring to hear you are in another World, I conclude for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Anno Domini, <hi>1677.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Of whoſe contrivance can you think this Letter was, what could be the deſign of it? I am ſatisfied <hi>(Sir)</hi> my Wife contriv'd it, it is certain, ſhe ſent it to her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> to be there tranſcribed, and ſent it up by the Poſt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected as above. I ſuppoſe you will take it as a magical Prediction of what was intended, <hi>viz.</hi> the laying a Baſtard to my charge for a farther pretence of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for <hi>(Sir)</hi> ſhe knew the Wench was of ill fame, and had layn at a ſuſpected Houſe, before ſhe procured her Siſter to hire her for me; my Wife had a corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency with the Wench whilſt ſhe lived with me, met her ſeveral times. And <hi>Sir,</hi> is it not ſtrange that my Wife (who for eighteen Months before was not to be heard of,) ſhould within four days after this Wench was brought to Bed, (if there was any ſuch matter) find out the Wench, examine her with ſo much cunning and patience, and ſo unconcernedly endure to be told that her Husband was ſo familiar with her nine Months, without leaving ſome marks upon her?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> The Wench lived not above ten Months in all with me, of which my Couſin Mr. <hi>William Cage</hi> was my conſtant Bedfellow for four Months before ſhe went away, and never lodged from me. I had warn'd her away in <hi>March,</hi> ſhe went away in <hi>June,</hi> and had the Baſtard (if any) in <hi>January</hi> following: 'tis not probable, that after the Wench had taken warning to be gone, ſhe ſhould be willing, nor yet that I ſhould venture after Mr. <hi>Cramer</hi> gave me notice of her haunting Bawdyhouſes.</p>
            <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my Wif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:8"/> ſeveral Perſons as witneſſes for a pretence with her: And becauſe, when I heard of this damnable deſign againſt me, I reſolved to puniſh the Wench, and for that end gave to Mr. <hi>Winford</hi> in <hi>Fullers</hi> Rents (whoſe Cook Maid ſhe then was) ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to get a Warrant, and to ſet a watch upon her that ſhe ſhould not get away before the matter was examined before a Magiſtrate. But my Wife gave her ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſit, pretending to ſearch the Baſtard for a Mole I had on my Body, which no Perſon knew but my Wife, and this mark ſhe acquainted the Woman of the Houſe with, that the Wench might the better pretend to a familiar acquaintance with me. <hi>Sir,</hi> This Wench on the ſudden (to prevent my bringing the matter to a full examination) was conveyed away, without either my will or knowledge, and whither I know not, or whether there ever was any Baſtard of that Wenches, (as pretended) I know not, nor did I ever hear that the Wench was with Child until this Baſtard Plot was diſcovered. And <hi>Sir,</hi> although my Wife hath ſeveral times declared in ſeveral places, and to me afterwards, that ſhe had ſearched to the bottom of the buſineſs, and was ſatisfied I was wronged in that matter, yet I have ever ſince laid out to have this Wench taken; I have offered five Pounds to effect it, and will now give the ſame Sum to have her taken, that the matter may come into Judgment publickly; nay <hi>Sir,</hi> I have ſued, and do now ſue in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Court a Conſort of my Wifes for it, that the truth may appear; nor cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, would any man think me ſo ſilly as not to have prevented the diſgrace, by providing otherwiſe for the Whore, and in a more remote place than <hi>Fullers</hi> Rents was, which joyns to <hi>Grays-Inn;</hi> where the Libel ſaith, the Whore was lodged for neighboured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I would not have inſiſted ſo much upon this mean matter, but that my Wife uſed it as her <hi>Achilean</hi> argument to juſtifie her treacherous departing from me, notwithſtanding ſhe was gone from me eighteen Months before.</p>
            <p>As to thoſe falſities of turning my Wife out of doors, and bidding my Servant to ſhut the door upon her, and threatning to fire the Houſe over her head: Thus I ſay, when I bought the houſe at <hi>Highgate</hi> for her, and had drawn the Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ready, ſhe refuſed to pay for it according to her agreement, nor had I any Money of hers in my hands, or to command, to pay for it, I having at that time laid out above 400 <hi>l.</hi> in Suites at Law in her concerns, as Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barrington,</hi> who were ſent on the ſudden to view my Books, found: Mr. <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> then caſt up my Book and ſigned it. I did, as I remember, bid my Servant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint her, then (as the truth was) that I was ſued in an Ejectment for that Houſe, and that I had covenanted that ſhe or her Truſtee ſhould pay the Money, or I would deliver poſſeſſion of the Houſe by ſuch a day, if ſhe did not the one or the other, ſhe would be turned out of poſſeſſion: But I do not remember, nor can I believe that I ever did threaten the firing of another Mans Houſe, ſo penal by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Law, no leſs than Felony: And I do ſolemnly proteſt, that from the firſt day of my Marriage to this very time, I did never turn her, or cauſe her to be turned out of any Houſe or Place where I lived, or the door to be ſhut againſt her: But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue it is, after ſhe had diſturbed me in my buſineſs at <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> and I provided a Lodging for her, I lock'd my Chamber door, and when ſhe had left the Houſe at <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ighgate,</hi> and taken away and ſold ſeveral of my Goods, bought with my own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:38311:8"/> Chairs of my Parlour, and other things, I did then indeed forbid my Servant to ſuffer her or her Daughter any more to ranſack the Houſe. As to any Servant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying her otherwiſe entrance or admittance unto me, where ever I was, or at any hour, none ever durſt be ſo ſaucy, or had any ſuch orders. As to Mr. <hi>Middletons</hi> endeavouring to introduce her, and ſending Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> to acquaint me with it, and that I refuſed it, there is nothing more falſe; for Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> knows that when I heard that he was perſwading her to return to her duty, and that ſhe refuſed it, and went away on Foot toward <hi>Highgate,</hi> I was greatly troubled, and ſent Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> one way, and my Clerk another, a third Perſon another, to bring her back if poſſibly; nor did I ever take or keep any Woman-ſervant againſt her conſent, otherwiſe than is hereafter ſet forth. When ſhe abſented her ſelf from me for eighteen Months together, and at laſt returned home, with a deſign to have a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantage againſt me, then I having a Servant-maid who lived with me about ſix Months, and one Year before with her; and my Wife deſiring to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce another, who lived in the Houſe where ſhe was concealed from me all that time, and of the Plot as I concluded, ſhe, I ſay, deſiring I would turn my Maid-ſervant away, and admit of hers: I acknowledge I did refuſe it, but declared that if ſhe would take a meer Stranger to all the differences, I would turn her away, otherwiſe I would keep them both, that ſhe deſired to introduce, and that I had, that I might have one Perſon that might teſtifie for my Carriage, as well as ſhe one for hers: and this the righteous God knows was all the deſign I had in keeping of that Maid-ſervant; and as ſoon as my Wife had provided <hi>Elizabeth Gun</hi> that was ſuch a Stranger, (nay, I think ſooner,) I turn'd my Maid away: Nor did I ever endeavour any ways to weaken the Marriage Articles, if ſhe would live with me as a Wife, but endeavoured to have them decreed according to the intent and meaning thereof; which was, that an equitable proportion of the profits of the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> might be ſet out for her maintenance with me, and the reſidue thereof (after her Debts paid, and my juſt disburſements for the maintenance and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Children, and in Suites at Law in defence of her, and occaſioned by her) ſhould be given to her Children upon their preferment in Marriage. I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in my Bill (which was commenc'd <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term 1674) I lay the cauſe of our Suites (but not the firſt differences) upon Doctor <hi>Paget,</hi> and I ſtill do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the ſame. It is true, when ſhe abſented her ſelf for eighteen Months toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I not knowing where to find her, to reduce her to a ſociety with me as a Wife, the Marriage-ſettlement being made to ſecure her maintenance <hi>in cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as a Wife,</hi> and ſhe had broke her Marriage vows with me by her abſence, I did deliver to ſeveral Perſons Papers to prohibit their receiving her, or paying her any Money; yet at the ſame time gave private inſtruction to Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> to ſupply her, and not to let her want. I deny that my Bill in <hi>Chancery</hi> was ever condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for being ſcandalous or impertinent by any Maſter whatſoever; but true it is, Sir <hi>Miles Cock</hi> (as I am informed) did tax 12 <hi>l.</hi> coſt, without ſummoning me, to be paid to Doctor <hi>Paget</hi> upon my exceptions to his inſufficient Anſwer, for ſaying, my Wife abſented her ſelf from me by the inſtigation of the Devil, and the Doctor the Defendant, but I believe ſuch Coſts were never taxed befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38311:9"/> 
               <hi>Paget</hi> to reward him in that kind for his ill advice, I need not, I have had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity enough. For <hi>Stedman,</hi> I believe I have ſaid, no Gentleman would have adviſed a Wife to ſeparate her ſelf from her Husband, to maintain a Bill againſt him in the name of another man, and that his Wife and Children too hath more cauſe to complain than my Wife. For Mr. <hi>Jenner,</hi> another of her Counſel, I deny that ever I ſaw him to my knowledge, or that ever I wrote a Sentence, Letter, ot Note to him; for all the reſt of that Slander, there is no part of it true: Nor did I ever deſire Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> of <hi>Hackney</hi> to acquaint her capricious Friend with the differences, for I did never think him a man either of Brains or good will enough to do any good office between me and my Wife, which long ſince appear'd, but more particularly now of late, as follows: Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> met this pretended Friend upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and moved to him, that there might be ſome end put to the differences between Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Wife, any end were better then none: The pious Friend replies, There can be no end. Certainly this upſtart Dictators Decree is not unlike that advice given to the treacherous <hi>Cateline</hi> by the Ghoſt of factious <hi>Scylla</hi> (one of the Council of State in the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth,) <hi>The evils thou haſt done cannot be ſafe without attempting greater:</hi> So here, <hi>there can be no end</hi> (ſays he) according to the modern principle, <hi>When the Sword is drawn againſt the Head, throw away the Scabbard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> 'Tis a thing impoſſible to anſwer this Libel in any method, becauſe it is confuſedly, and diſorderly, aſwell as maliciouſly pen'd: Sometimes the Friend is mentioned in one place, ſometimes in another, and ſo in ſeveral places, That a Gentleman ſeeing this Libel in my Chamber, concluded by the Stile, that the ſame Pen that wrote <hi>The Worlds Miſtake in</hi> Oliver Cromwel, wrote this. But now to apply wholly to the divorcing Friend, I do (as the Libel ſays) lay the whole blame of the difference upon him, not for the reaſon of lending his Name (to ſue me before he diſcourſed me,) but for maliciouſly endeavouring a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome conſiderable time before the differences broke out; for Mr. <hi>Abraham Barrington</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the firſt Mediator for our reconciliation, before any Bill in <hi>Chancery</hi> was filed on either ſide, at <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Tide 1674, (when his Family was in the Country,) appointed us to meet him at his houſe in <hi>Suffolk-Lane</hi> for priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that we might have liberty to talk our Bellies full, (as he himſelf expreſſed it:) Meet we did there, but I confeſs I durſt not enter the liſts, (ſhe always worſting me at that;) therefore ſhe being in one Room and my ſelf in another, I intreated Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> to deal with us ſeverally there: As one of my principal grievances, I complained that this Perſon had ſowed diſſention, endeavoured a breach, and that my Wife her ſelf had told me he had uſed this expreſſion to her at my Houſe in my abſence; <hi>Is this your man of diſcretion, to make Walks here, and no longer time in the Houſe?</hi> Another time, <hi>What did you marry this</hi> Cage <hi>for? if you had ſtayed I had married you, I have</hi> 800 <hi>l.</hi> per annum. I was afterwards frequently upbraided with what a Fortune ſhe had loſt for me. <hi>Sir,</hi> his ſaying this to my Wife was occaſioned by my deſiring her to forbear his company, ſhe having diſcovered to me his principles and uſual diſcourſe of Perſons, not fit to be rendred in ſuch Characters by any Engliſhman; to my diſturbance, many times when I came home, for I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> diſcourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sir</hi> I confeſs their wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:9"/> made then alſo, was, that ſhe would abandon this pretended Friend: which ſhe refuſing before Mr. <hi>Barrington,</hi> I then charged her to forbear his company. This alſo, <hi>Sir,</hi> was long before any Suite, I ſay, 'twas in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1674. Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> uſed long and earneſt endeavours of reconciliation, until the beginning of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas</hi> Term: And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſee how obliging my Wife was to me; inſtead of abandonding his company, ſhe viſits him at his Chamber frequently, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly goes abroad with him in affront to me, forſakes my company wholly, and ſends railing, lying Letters, which I have by me, to one of which ſhe ſubſcribes my Name, and ſtrikes a daſh through it thus, <hi>Cage.</hi> One day meeting her at Mr. <hi>Doelittles,</hi> where ſhe took Sanctuary, and communicated with his Hearers in the height of this malice. I would have taken her home with me. She ſends for a Conſtable to have me before the Lord Mayor, and before ſhe came before him, ſhe ran away; and ſhe then (at Mr. <hi>Doelittles</hi>) told me, ſhe would keep this Friend company in ſpight of me, and declared the ſame at another time to Mr. <hi>Creamer.</hi> Mr. <hi>Barrrington</hi> prevailed with her at the beginning of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term to come and dine at my Chamber. I then alſo told her my diſſatisfaction touching the deſign of this Friend, and begged of her (with all the fervency of my ſoul) to abandon him; after this was named, ſhe would not by any means ſtay with me that night, which Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> cannot but remember. <hi>Sir,</hi> before the end of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term I entreated her to let me know what the matter was why ſhe was ſo unjuſt, for I ſolemnly proteſt I did not know; nay her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> knows, and hath told it to divers, that I once gave her a Pen, Ink, and Paper, and bid her write what ſhe would, touching her Eſtate, and it ſhould be done; but ſhe would not. The next news I heard of my Wife (inſtead of complying with me) was, that this precious Friend had in affront to me, brought a Bill in his own name againſt me, for and on the behalf of my Wife, therein abuſing me, complaining falſly I had altered the Marriage-ſettlement, and ſcandalouſly alledges that my Wife had no Child by me, and we were parted, (as my Wife calls it in her Libel;) which I never knew of, nor agreed unto, nor ever will. I am now on ſuch a Subject, that I know not when I ſhould leave it; if I ſhould ſuffer my ſelf to tell you all the unworthineſs of theſe two precious Friends, how the one hath anſwered her Marriage vows, and the other the profeſſion of Piety he makes. I will only add this in anſwer to that part of the Libel, that ſays I ſo much deſired the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of that Friend, but really I never did ſo but once at dinner, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I knew him, and that in kindneſs to my Wife, being deſirous to ſhew reſpect to all Perſons ſhe called Friends, when I firſt married her; I have ever ſince avoided him as much as I could; I never took him to be a man fit for the ſociety of any but of his own humor, his converſe being only of the Rapines and Ruines of the late Times and Perſons, his own diſſatisfaction, and quarrelling with thoſe above him. The next, <hi>Sir,</hi> is to ſhew you what unhappineſs and miſery this Woman was (as ſhe alledged in her Libel) aſhamed to acquaint this Friend of hers with. <hi>Sir,</hi> this Woman having for ſeveral Years laid her Snares for a conſiderable Prey, miſſing the greater, would have taken up with a Mechanick; ſhe loſt her labour there, but at laſt enſnared the Man, well read as ſhe alledges in <hi>Machiavel.</hi> For three or four Years ſo kind and hypocritically obliging ſhe was, that all the World muſt know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:10"/> his buſineſs, and ſpent all his time (but that of dallying with, and careſſing her,) in ſecuring her ſhattered Eſtate to make her Children happy, gave them all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Education, and was ſo kind to them that their own Fathers could not have been kinder; gave her liberty to diſpoſe of her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> ſhe brought, for her ſelf and Children; provided more than ſhe deſired for her and them, and never asked her for any accompt of Money he ſent; but when what he had ſent was gone, ſhe had more: but yet (as ſhe declared) the truth was ſhe did not know what ſhe ailed, ſhe wanted nothing, yet ſhe could not be content: This is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs for the firſt three or four Years, that ſhe was aſhamed to acquaint this precious Friend with, as you will ſee by the Proofs at the latter end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Pray ſee when this miſery began. At the four Years end her Husband find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Children grew marriageable, and although that which was deſperate of her own Eſtate her Husband had ſecured by Suites, yet becauſe it would not be readily paid if her Children had offers of preferment, her Husband ſecured 800 <hi>l.</hi> to her Children, 700 <hi>l.</hi> thereof by undeniable City-ſecurity, payable one the day of Marriage, and in the mean time the Intereſt is paid to the Cildren for their maintenance, and the Bond written in the Childrens names, and delivered to them, of which 800 <hi>l.</hi> there was but 100 <hi>l.</hi> part of the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> nor of her Eſtate. Next, her Husband at the expence of very great Sums of Money obtained a Decretal Order for a 100 <hi>l. per annum</hi> for her life, which ſhe had loſt, nay releaſed: her Husband had done all this, and maintained and educated her Children without waſting any of the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> ſtill remaining, but what ſhe her ſelf ſpent. Thus the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> whereof five was deſperate, being made good by Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> by expenceful Suites, 700 <hi>l.</hi> ſettled on the Children, a 100 <hi>l. per annum</hi> for her Life, and in all probability 500 <hi>l.</hi> at leaſt Arrears ſecured: Now was the time to ſet up the Deed, and for the Truſtee to enter upon the Truſt now; and never before, did ſhe pretend to more at her diſpoſe than the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> but now ſhe would ſeparate, before her Husband had got in any part of this Eſtate to recompence any of his disburſements, either for her, the Suites, or for, or to her Children: now ſhe brags that her Children had 800 <hi>l.</hi> ſettled on them, ſhe had her own Eſtate, with the 100 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and 500 <hi>l.</hi> Arrears; now for a ſeparation of Perſons, and Eſtate would follow.</p>
            <p>Now her miſery began indeed, this addition to the Eſtate made her talk ſhe might have deſerved her precious Friend with his 800 <hi>l. p. an.</hi> and a better man than he. Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> if he had known what would have followed, would have had her, for he was only afraid of her Children, and as things fall out, ſhe had brought him a better Portion than his Wife he now hath. And truly, from that very time ſhe may date her miſery, for from that time ſhe grew ſo intollerably proud, and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no Servant could pleaſe her, nor Child be ſervile or Slave enough; and her Husband that unhappily had made the Eſtate ſo conſiderable, was now ſet at naught. Here began her extremity of cruelty to her Children; from reproving her for that, her abuſing her Husband; from thence Collonel <hi>Birch,</hi> Dr. <hi>Paget,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Okey,</hi> hearing the difference, Dr. <hi>Paget</hi> not then juſtly complying with Collonel <hi>Birch</hi> and Mr. <hi>Okey,</hi> adviſing her not to return home, but let her Husband bite on the Bridle, adding, We will choak him with the Judgment: to which end Dr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:10"/> her to one of <hi>Lincolns-Inn,</hi> who encouraged her, and told her the general words of the Deed excluded her Husband if he ſhould have afterwards diſcovered and recovered 15000 <hi>l.</hi> more than the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> intended by that Deed: This vain conceit made her and her precious Friends ſwell like <hi>Lucifer;</hi> thus ſprung her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and henceforward, ſhe that was not able before to educate her Children, now ſhould have no need of an Husband; her Children in this five Years well educated by her Husband, her Eſtate thus increaſed, ſhe and her Friend would make her Husband truckle. From this time nothing but occaſions of ſeparation was ſought for. Then when I ſought to her for Peace, ſhe told, No, you complained of my cruelty to my Children, the World ſhall now ſee, that I value my Children before you. And about this time Mr. <hi>Creamer,</hi> Mr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> the Miniſter, and Mr. <hi>Doelittle</hi> (I not preſent) diſcourſed her touching a Reconciliation, ſhe declared, No, let them do what they would with the Eſtate, but ſhe would never live with her Husband, (then ſhe never pretended whoring,) then ſhe only pretended ſhe durſt not live with me, I had offered to ſtab her with Sizars, another time to cut her Throat, which I wonder ſhe hath omitted in the Libel, but (the Lord knows) I never then offered her the leaſt unlawful violence, nor afterwards indeed, that might juſtly be ſo termed.</p>
            <p>Then began ſhe firſt to abſent her ſelf, and hence follow all the Provocations to a Separation, in the Proofs annexed. But to return again to the pretended Friend, he goes with her, and retains Sir <hi>Francis Winnington</hi> Counſel for her; who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily would not receive any Fee, but upon theſe Terms, That they would refer the matter to him, and if Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> would do ſo too, he would make an end of the Buſineſs. This was the Reference before mentioned, wherein ſhe falſly accuſed me of Adultery with Mrs. <hi>Price.</hi> Sir <hi>Francis</hi> upon ſeveral Meetings examining the Matter, and the Truſtee <hi>Okey</hi> himſelf reproved my Wife very plainly, and told her that ſhe deſerved to be bound to the good Behaviour, drew up the Heads of his Award in writing with his own hand, and deliver'd it to the Truſtee to acquaint my Wife with, which was as follows, That the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> made known to Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> before the Deed was ſealed, ſhould be made good according to the Marriage; and for the reſt that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> had ſince diſcovered, and recovered by Suits, he ought to have. And thereupon I deſired, as my free Gift, that Sir <hi>Francis</hi> would award five hundred more out of the Iriſh Arrears, which at my Requeſt he alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. This being ſhewed to her, ſhe and her Friend contrives a Revocation of Sir <hi>Francis Winnington</hi>'s Power, and ſent it to him before the Award was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in due form, whereby a Period was put to all thoſe Endeavours. Then this Woman begins to rail at Sir <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> and her Friend threatens me in a Notice left with my Clerk of his own hand-writing. Then a Reference was had to Sir <hi>Fr. Winnigton</hi> again, and Mr. <hi>Creamer,</hi> which ſhe made fruitleſs; then to Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> and Mr. <hi>Creamer,</hi> they reſolv'd on every particular, as well touching her Behaviour for the future, as the Eſtate, and put them into writing, thoſe I ſign'd, but ſhe refuſed. <hi>Note,</hi> all theſe Perſons were of her own nomination, and Friends. But I omitted to mention the Reference to Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> of <hi>Hackney,</hi> her Brother in Law, and Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> her Truſtèe; they agreed ſeveral, if not all the particular Differences, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhe refuſed to abide by, reflecting uncivilly upon them. After this ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:11"/> Baſtard, more particularly to Madam <hi>Broughton</hi> and the Lady <hi>Liſle,</hi> and lived above a year with me. And indeed ſhe might well be ſatisfied when ſhe was the Foundation of that Slander. But ſhe not having advantage enough againſt me before ſhe went from me; for ſhe and her Friend had adviſed with Civilians for a Divorce, and it was told ſhe could not have it but for Adultery or Cruelty; for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery ſhe was ſure, and hath often declared, ſhe ſhould never have that for a Cauſe, and therefore to provoke me to ſome act of Severiy ſhe continues at home, and pretends ſhe was ſorry ſhe had gone away, ſhe was adviſed to it by — her Friend and his Counſel. With what Joy I received her, ſhe and others know well, and that I treated her with all the kindneſs imaginable; and for her greater obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhe deſiring to have her Children live with her, I took another Houſe for her at <hi>Thiſtleworth,</hi> furniſhed it all at my own Charge, took Servants for her, and lived there with her. And that all Cauſes of Difference for the future, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it might be taken away, I deſired her to think of ſome Lawyer of Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Integrity, to ſettle all things as they ought to be upon the true Baſis of Juſtice and Equity. She names Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> of the Temple, in the Libel menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, who had always been of Counſel with her long before I married her, and married an intimate Acquaintance of hers: I agreed to it, and attended him with an Order in Chancery by conſent, whereby all Matters in difference were referred to him. Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> knows I then told him, <hi>Sir, we have both pitcht upon you to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our Breaches, here is the Caſe, do as you would be done unto, if the Caſe were yours, I will not reſtrain you, you ſhall not diſpleaſe me.</hi> This I often afterward declared to him, particularly before Mr. <hi>Thornton</hi> the Earl of <hi>Bedford</hi>'s Chaplain, and Madam <hi>Broughton,</hi> and by this I thought my ſelf ſecured from any further Troubles and Diſquiets from my Wife, and indeed ſhe began to be obliging. But Sir, <hi>Betty Blackwel</hi> her own Daughter coming again to live with us, pretended frequent Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of going to <hi>London,</hi> of which I muſt know nothing, ſometimes going in the Morning betimes, Letters and Whiſperings when ſhe came home of great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, my ſelf and Houſe neglected; of this I took little notice, my Wife grew ſtrange, nothing of kindneſs from her. One day being greatly troubled, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed mildly with her, ſaying, <hi>Wife, what is the matter? how comes this Change? other Women are more kind to their Husbands.</hi> She replied, <hi>She could be no otherwiſe, I might help my ſelf if I could.</hi> Sir, I was amazed, I found Affronts daily from her and her Daughter; the Reaſon I knew not, they wanted nothing, the Money for the Houſe the Daughter kept, never without ten or twenty Pounds, they did what they pleaſed, I never demanded an Account to this day. This, <hi>Elizabeth Gun</hi> who then lived with us, and now lives with Mr. <hi>Gun</hi> at <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> can inform you. On Friday-night my Wife began to ſtorm bitterly, for my ſaying, That it would have become her Daughter to have told me that ſhe was going to <hi>London,</hi> and I had deſerved more Civility than that. The Storm grew ſo great, that I roſe from Bed, where I then was, and walk'd all Night in the Garden. The next day I croſt the <hi>Thames,</hi> to wander for quietneſs ſake, and met in the Afternoon on <hi>Richmond</hi> Hill Mr. <hi>Thankeful Owen,</hi> whom I engaged to give me a Viſit next day at my Houſe, by which I hoped to lay the Devil; that ſucceeded, and had effect for about a fortnight. But the Daughter going to <hi>London</hi> again, when ſhe came home <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:11"/> attend my Buſineſs. Term came on, Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> did nothing, though importun'd by me. Her precious Friend came alſo to Town, whom upon my taking the Houſe at <hi>Thiſtleworth</hi> ſhe promiſed me never to converſe with, or ſee again, if ſhe could avoid it: but ſhe that never kept Promiſe with me, no not her Marriage Vows, could not forbear but muſt go to him for Counſel, as ſhe her ſelf owned. And what Counſel ſhe had, judge by the Effects following. I was often told of her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Friends Lodging, I blam'd her for it; ſhe told me, let me help my ſelf; I replied, I would upon him, though I could not upon her. This made her rage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerably, ſo that neither Day nor Night I could have reſt, as the ſame <hi>Elizabeth Gun</hi> can inform you; ſhe knows I have been forced to riſe out of my Bed, and ſit up whole Nights, ſometimes in Mr. <hi>Morgan</hi>'s Chamber in <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> ſometimes at Mr. <hi>Fairberds,</hi> ſometimes lock up my ſelf in my Study all Night, then ſhe would break my Windows, ſaying, <hi>Turn me out then, turn me out of Doors.</hi> She once rail'd me firſt out of the Bed, followed me out of one Room into another, then going out into the Court purſued me, crying, <hi>Rogue, Baſtard, thy Father and Mother were Baſtards,</hi> and miſcalling my firſt Wife by ſuch Names which I can't in Modeſty mention, and that I murder'd her. This was at Midnight. I confeſs I turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her with a mind to have laid her at my foot, but I had not the Heart to ſtrike her, but betook me to my Heels to run from her; ſhe followed me cloſe round about the Court again and again, till I was ready to ſink. From this I ſee ſhe deſigned to provoke me, either to turn her violently out of Doors, or do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing cruel againſt her in paſſion, that ſhe might have a pretext of ſeparation, or living aſunder at her liberty. I ſent Madam <hi>Broughton</hi> to her, alſo Mr. <hi>Fairbeard,</hi> who deſired her to remove out of my Chamber to a Lodging at my charge, that I might have my Chamber quiet for my buſineſs, but ſhe would not, but being afraid that I ſhould revenge my ſelf on her precious Friend, She perjured her ſelf to bind me to the Peace, takes my Lord Chief Juſtice's Warrant, a Tipſtaff, and Mr. <hi>Powels</hi> man, one <hi>Sorrel,</hi> who comes for me at eight of the Clock at night, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing I could not get Bail ſo late at night, and that I muſt ly in cuſtody that night (being <hi>Saturday</hi>) and that next day, for want of Bail. I being not in the way, Mr. <hi>Powel</hi>'s man waits for me to give the Tipſtaff notice when I ſhould come in; this I believe was the occaſion of his being pumpt (if he was) the next time he came, for I never call'd out Bayliffs, nor did I know he was pumpt, until my Wife told me it was done, and if any Perſon ſwore any ſuch thing, I believe he was ſuborned by her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Seeing I could not prevail with her to leave my Chamber, I removed my ſelf, and left her there; firſt, to Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> in <hi>Bawldwins-Garden,</hi> next to another Chamber in <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> where I lodged to my great damage in my practice, until her own Brother Captain <hi>Roſe</hi> came to Town, who being made ſenſible by her own Friends of her Miſcarriages, at laſt prevailed with her to remove to a Lodging at <hi>Grays-Inn-gate,</hi> which I had long before taken for her at 20 <hi>l. per annum;</hi> and indeed he ſo diſcreetly managed the buſineſs, that he brought us together to lodge and keep Houſe there, which we did until the Saturday before <hi>Whitſontide</hi> laſt: but ſhe ſtill retained her deſign of provoking me to give matter of divorce for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended cruelty, and endeavoored it; ſo that I was there forced, ſometimes to riſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:12"/> this way of provocation, ſhe put this device in practice. I had appointed to go out of Town with her and her Daughter, for all the <hi>Whitſon</hi>-week for the Air, which they agreed unto; <hi>Saturday</hi> after dinner was appointed, I came from my Chamber to bid them get ready, but ſhe and her Daughter were gone, whither, or with whom, I could not learn, nor when they would return: I ſupp'd, lodg'd, din'd next day, and ſo till <hi>Wedneſday</hi> morning, and then I left a Note in writing at the Lodging, to this purport:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wife, This is a new ſort of provocation, I am retired to my Chamber; if when you come home you write me word where you have been, with whom, and why you dealt thus unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by me, I will come to you, but till then I will never meet you at that Lodging where you have put ſuch an affront upon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday</hi>-night ſhe comes to the Lodging alone without her Daughter, takes no notice of me, or what I wrote, goes away again and ſtays till <hi>Saturday,</hi> never gives me any account where ſhe was, or with whom; ſends indeed for me one day to dinner by a Girl of the Houſe; I returned, I could not, until ſhe gave me the ſatisfaction I deſired. A day or two after a Gentleman of <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> Society informed me ſhe was in the Walks the day before, walking with this Friend: This <hi>Sir,</hi> (I hope you will believe) could not but provoke a Porter; but <hi>Sir,</hi> the next day after, I walking in the Walks, ſee my Wife ſitting with the Lady Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> I call'd her to me, demanded of her what ſhe and that Friend intended to walk in that familiar manner under my Noſe, they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent theſe provocations, and 'twas ſuch a piece of Impudence, that no vertuous Woman would have offered againſt the honour of a Husband; ſhe gave me ſome baſe Language, but out of reſpect to the Lady Marqueſs, I proteſt I departed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further wrangling; nor did I otherwiſe than is here ſet down treat my Wife, neither did I ever ſee her at any other time in the Lady Marqueſſes preſence. Since this time, my Wife would never give me the ſatisfaction to know where ſhe was, nor with whom, in that <hi>Whitſon</hi>-week. But this indeed, a Woman whom my Wife hath prevailed withall to depart from her Husband alſo, one full as wicked, (though not ſo cunning as her ſelf,) and of my knowledge a notorious Slanderer, did once ſay, ſhe knew my Wife was with no man at that time. This <hi>Sir,</hi> if there be truth in man, this was her laſt parting (as ſhe calls it) from me, without any cauſe given her. Therefore, ſee what a Wife I have, that will for twelve Months together thus grieve her Husband, rather than give him ſo eaſie a ſatisfaction; ſurely, there is no Perſon but muſt conclude, that either ſhe cannot diſcover with reputation to her honour the Perſons and Place where ſhe then was, or elſe that ſhe is well pleaſed in this ſeparation, and that this laſt affront and provocation hit her deſign, though others failed. <hi>Sir,</hi> till <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> laſt I paid for her Lodging, and then declared, I would not for the future, unleſs ſhe would give account of the <hi>Whitſon</hi>-week, which ſhe hath not yet done. <hi>Sir,</hi> I know not what words are in every Letter I have wrote to her in anſwer to her railing Accuſations, and perhaps I might ſometime in Term-time have deſired her by Letter not to trouble my Chamber with ſcolding and brawling, for you may believe I would never have kept my Chamber in the Inn, which I can lett for 20 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and keep Lodgings for her beſides at 20 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> if I could live quietly with her in either, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:38311:12"/> married her: But the diſturbance I received from her in my Chamber, which I made convenient for her, and intending her company there only in the depth of Winter, was not tollerable, as too many of the Society well know. And now <hi>Sir,</hi> what a Friend this precious Friend has been to us both (as ſhe pretends,) leaving the deciſion of the differences he created, to <hi>Chancery,</hi> judge by Mr. <hi>Thomas Danſon</hi> the Miniſters depoſition, and whether I did not intend fairly by the offers Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> made him on my behalf, in order to a ſpeedy and right deciſion of the pretended difference, whatever the Libel pretends. And <hi>Sir,</hi> for the laſt order of Reference, which ſhe ſays I refuſed, I acknowledge that it being pen'd different from the other order, to include the wrongs the pretended Friend had done me, in miſleading my Wife, cauſing this ſeparation, fomenting and maintaining theſe quarrels between me and my Wife, I did refuſe to refer theſe wrongs to the arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Mr. <hi>Powel;</hi> yet at the ſame time, I my ſelf, my Council, and my Clerk in <hi>Chancery</hi> did ſign the ſame order, with exception only of the wrongs the pretended Friend had done me, and ſuch Actions and rights of Action as I then had againſt him, for I do aver, the firſt difference between my Wife and I aroſe from my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring my Wife to forbear his company, becauſe of his cenſorious, dangerous, and malecontent Spirit, for which he took a ſpleen, and then told her, he would have married her if ſhe had ſtayed. And after I had publickly forbidden her his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he brought this Bill in his own name, without any cauſe, and in affront to me, which is prohibited by ſeveral Statute Laws, he being no way concerned, either as Truſtee, or otherwiſe than as a Fomenter of the Quarrel: For which, and other wrongs he hath done me, I have brought my Action, and laid the damages in the Libel, and will have it poſſibly firſt or laſt of him, ſuch a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of ſatisfaction as is fit for a Gentleman ſo much abuſed to have. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, this Woman (the ſhame of her Sex) by her Libel contemns the power and worth of her Huband, with regard to this perfidious Friend, and ſays this Libel is only to ſhew how little credit or belief is to be given to her Husbands ſuggeſtions, or indeed oaths. But <hi>Sir,</hi> her Husband needs not to make oath; read but the Proofs and Oaths of others annexed, I hope they are not all ſuch Perſons. as this perfidious Wife would have her Husband to be.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Sir,</hi> as to the pretended beating of her, I once more ſolemnly proteſt, I never did, or offered any unkind or unlawful violence to her Perſon, until ſhe had abſented her ſelf from me for about eighteen Months, nor until ſhe was returned home with a deſign of provocation, and firſt ſtroke me on the face in the preſence of her Neece Mrs. <hi>Iſabel Roſe,</hi> and one <hi>Mary Bucknal;</hi> her Neece is indeed gone to <hi>Barbadoes</hi> to her Father, but hath left a ſufficient teſtimony behind of that matter with Perſons of credit: I confeſs I then gave her one box on the Ear with my open Hand, and <hi>Sir,</hi> ought not that in juſtice be deemed rather a moderate correction I was obliged unto, for the reſtraining her from ſuch like impudent attempts hereafter, than any unlawful violence or cruelty? Could that <hi>Socrates</hi> his patience, or any more Chriſtian have done leſs in ſuch a provocation, without emboldening her hereafter to contemn a Husband. But I ever till then accounted it ſo diſhonourable to offer any violence to a Woman, that I never could, or ever did th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like before: nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:13"/> And certainly, had here been a little Honeſty mixt with the profeſſion of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorcing <hi>Jew,</hi> there had been no attempts and ſtruglings to break the peace and unity of a Family, united by the Ordinance of God; <hi>If you had ſtayed, I had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried you, and I have</hi> 800 <hi>l. a Year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray obſerve this Paſſage of the Libel, <hi>After her patient waiting on the References two Years, then and not before, ſhe moved to have my Demur to her Friends Bill argued.</hi> Sir, ſee the patience ſhe pretends unto. In <hi>Hillary</hi> Term 1676, ſhe brings two other Bills againſt me, one in the Truſtee's name, another in the name of one <hi>Wilſon. Wilſon</hi> I anſwered; that Cauſe was heard the 12th of <hi>June</hi> 1677, at which hearing, the Lord Chancellour ſuſpended the ſettling the Cauſe upon the merits, until the Truſtee <hi>Okey's</hi> Bill was brought to hearing, and to that end, that all the matters in difference between her, my ſelf, and the Truſtee may receive a full ſettlement. It was decreed the Truſtee do amend his Bill, and make the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Parties, and bring the Cauſe to hearing in <hi>Hillary</hi> Term following, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued 300 <hi>l.</hi> in Court towards my ſatisfaction. At the hearing of the Cauſe, ſhe and her precious Friend finding I was like to have Juſtice on hearing <hi>Okeys</hi> Cauſe, then indeed and not before brings on my Plea to the Friends Bill, put in three Years before, knowing that I would never anſwer that Bill to give her and him any colour of converſe, and by pretence of my not anſwering that Bill, ſhe hath ever ſince, and by other vexations, ſtayed the hearing of <hi>Okeys</hi> Cauſe, which would have ſettled all the matters long e're this; for I ſolemnly proteſt, I do not wave the anſwering that pretended Friends Bill, or any thing in it, but the <hi>Perſon,</hi> and that I would not encourage a converſe between them, I had ſo long ſince for the peace and ſafety of my Family prohibited by the power of a Huband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> For ſuing her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> I had good reaſon for it as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thers. <hi>Sir,</hi> my Wife had received before I married above <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> more than ever was granted to her; I was ſued at Law for part of it, I pleaded the Statute of Limitations of Actions in Bar of the Dukes Action: afterwards, a Bill in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> was brought againſt me and her for this Money; I drew a Plea of the Statute of Limitations to that Bill, carried the Plea to Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> who was her Counſel, gave him a Piece to peruſe it and fit it for her with me; he approv'd of it, I got it ingroſs'd, ſhe refuſed to joyn with me in it, (though her own Counſel approv'd it,) and when I ſaw ſhe would not joyn, I being altering it in my Study for my ſelf only, reſolving to put that in for my ſelf to prevent coſts, ſhe thereupon raged and broke my Windows, which for that time (to ſatisfie her) I omitted putting in. At <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term following, a Serjeant at Arms was out for me and her, then 'twas too late to plead; But I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and finding all other the Duke's Counſel, as well as Sir <hi>John King</hi> who had ſigned the Bill in the Dukes name, were of her Counſel, and ſhe refuſing to joyn with me in the Plea her Counſel had allowed, which would certainly have put an end to the Suite; might not I, Sir, well ſuſpect that this Suite in the Duke's name was in truſt for her, and that ſhe had diſcovered and beg'd by ſome other name what ſhe had before received and concealed, and would now make me pay that Debt to her Friend, as if to the Duke? Therefore it was, <hi>Sir,</hi> that I brought this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> againſt the Dukes Grantee, <hi>Betty Blackwel,</hi> and ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:13"/> the Grantee of the Duke in truſt for my Wife. This <hi>Sir,</hi> was the reaſon (and no other) of my ſuing <hi>Betty Blackwel</hi> with others; nothwithſtanding, when her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had taken away my Goods from <hi>Thiſtleworth,</hi> and put only an old Petticoat of <hi>Betty Blackwels</hi> in the Bundle, which I had ſtopped by the way; ſhe goes to the Lord Chief Juſtice and complains I kept her Clothes, when I never knew ſhe had one Rag there, and got his Warrant to convene me before him, boaſted of it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly that ſhe had brought her Father before the Juſtice, as ſhe did one other time, that her Mother had ſet her Fathers Noſe awry: Was not this a barbarous action? Ingratitude in the higheſt! and is not the Mother like to make the Daughter as good as her ſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Two things pretended I had almoſt omitted; The one is, that I promiſed I would adopt her Daughter <hi>Okey</hi> for mine, for her Fathers ſake, with whom ('tis pretended) I had an intimate friendſhip. <hi>Sir,</hi> If there be truth in man, I never changed one Word with Collonel <hi>Okey</hi> but once, and that was only to have a Commiſſion for our County Troop to be renewed upon ſome of the changes of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor have ever ſpake or thought ill of the Man for any thing, but the Fact he died for, nor did I ever in any proceedings in <hi>Chancery</hi> or otherwiſe, blemiſh him or her upon his account, otherwiſe than by ſaying, that my marrying her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reproach of the manner of his death ought to have been an obligation to her, which no man that I ever yet met withall but will grant me; and how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable it is that I ſhould promiſe to adopt her Daughter, when I might expect Children of my own by her, and had made proviſion for her Children by the Deed to the Libel annexed, judge you?</p>
            <p>The other is, That, <hi>had my Husband deſigned nothing but what was juſt, the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of my Marriage-Articles might have long e're this been tryed by conſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I never oppoſed the performance of the Articles, nor ever will accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the true intent of them. And I do affirm that it never was intended, that I maintain her Suites and pay her debts concealed, nor could I bind my ſelf to be her Slave to recover an Eſtate not then mentioned to me, nor known to her ſelf, and that Deed can extend no further than unto the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> made known to me before the Deed of Settlement.</p>
            <p>But for the plauſible excuſe the Libel offers for the Friend, that there would be a Failer of Juſtice, if a Stranger might not ſue the Husband on the behalf of the Wife, when the Truſtee is either corrupted or weary of his truſt, eſpecially being Guardian to an Infant-party to the Articles: I anſwer, That if the Truſtee of the Wife ſhould die, leaving her Husband his Heir or Executor; there I confeſs there might be failer of Juſtice; becauſe if the Husband ſhould waſte the Eſtate which came to his Hands in truſt for his Wife, ſhe being a Perſon diſabled by Law to ſue her Husband in her own name, there I conceive it reaſonable that ſhe ſhould be permitted to ſue her Husband in the name of a third Perſon, for the preſervation and ſecurity of her Eſtate according to the truſt; But whilſt the Truſtee is in being he muſt ſue, and if he refuſe, it is the conſtant courſe of Equity to order one of the ſix Clerks, or ſome Relation of the Wife, to ſue in the Truſtees name, whether he will or no; or if the Truſtee be weary of his truſt, he himſelf may ſue to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged. But that a Perſon no way concern'd, but as a Contriver, Promoter, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:14"/> braided with it, one telling me ſhe was ſeen late at Night ſitting between her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Friend and his Secretary, like <hi>Suſanna</hi> between the two Elders, but ſhe did not look ſo innocently.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſhe hath Daughters which I hope may prove better Wives, therefore I ſpare her, yet I cannot wholly excuſe her from Blemiſhes. And I can with a good Conſcience reply, that for my Companions ſhe calls lewd, I never had a worſe than her ſelf. That ſhe liv'd with two former Husbands is true, with the one eight Months, with the other not four, yet with neither of them without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, although but Hony-Moon. And for five years ſhe did me that Right to ſay that I loved her; which you will find by the Proofs.</p>
            <p>For that Slander touching my Mother, I was dutiful, and ſhall carry the Proof of it to my Grave, having parted with at her Command 3500 <hi>l.</hi> of my own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as Mr. Serg. <hi>Connieres</hi> well knows, and that purely out of Love and Duty to her, and I do not know that ever I ſhewed any Irreverence to her in word or deed. And beſides this, every one of my Siſters hath had a better Portion of me, than my Wife and all her Siſters had together. It is true, I have one Siſter, who through her own Weakneſs and Inconſiderateneſs was reduced to Straits; her I took into my Houſe, and ſhe lived quietly and with reſpect to my former Wife ſixteen years, and was beloved by her; but after I married this Wife, I had no quiet till I turned her out of doors; ſince which I have and do ſupply her according to her Capacity, and that Ability my Wife hath left me, and do not know ſhe hath need of the Charity of any Perſon. But my Wife forgets her own ſavage hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of her own Mothers Ears. And as to my firſt Wife, and her Death, this is a Helliſh Inſinuation of her own Contrivance, falſe and malicious; but indeed ſhe endeavoured to ſubborn Mrs. <hi>Mary Husbands</hi> to Perjury, to diffame me in that. Read the Depoſition of Mrs. <hi>Mary Husbands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to that which ſhe pretends of Courtſhip with ſo conſiderable an Eſtate, certainly a Man of my years, and no Children, and a competent Employment need, not uſe ſuch Arguments for ſuch a Woman with two Children, and of ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; and that I, who never have lived above ten Miles from <hi>London,</hi> could ſo deceive her that had married two Husbands before, and had lived moſt of her time in <hi>London</hi> too, and had known me and my former Wife in my Troubles, as appears by Mr. <hi>Okeys</hi> Depoſition, is the moſt incredible thing imaginable. Sir, ſhe knew me in all the Changes of my Fortune, and all my Wives Relations four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years before, ſhe knew I was in conſiderable Buſineſs, and as likely as ſome other Men to be ſomething in the World; and without doubt I had ſo been, had I miſſed the Unhappineſs of marrying her, and thereby thoſe Interruptions and Diſtractions in my Buſineſs. But that I endeavoured to tempt her with any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments touching Eſtate, ſhe knows there is nothing more falſe. But I never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to any ſuch Eſtate after I knew her, never promiſed to ſettle any thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her. I did out of Conſcience and Honeſty, without any Requeſt of her, or any for her, ſettle her 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and ſecure it as fully as the Art of Man could contrive, for a Proviſion for her and her Children, and this I declared to Mr. <hi>Thomas Dun</hi> was my Reſolution to do before I married her.</p>
            <p>As touching my former Wife no Woman ever gave greater Teſtimony of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:14"/> and for her Satisfaction and Content with me, no Woman ever declared more: Of which this Wife found a Letter, ſent to me not two Months before ſhe died, with as great Expreſſions of Love and Unity as ever any Woman expreſſed. This Letter my now Wife obſerving me to read before I married her, and that the Kindneſs of the Expreſſions greatly moved me, ſhe got it away, and will never ſince produce it. But Sir, for that I refer you to her own Siſters, Mrs. <hi>Hannah</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Rebecca Fowks,</hi> who live at Mr. <hi>Buchanans</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> And for her Death, and indeed how we lived together, I alſo refer you to Dr. <hi>William Staynes,</hi> who was her Neighbour and Phyſician many years, who with Doctor <hi>Clerk</hi> his Kinſman opened and embowel'd her after her Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> There are ſome few things more will be expected I ſhould ſay ſomething unto, <hi>viz. That I permitted a Gentleman in</hi> Grays-Inn <hi>to abuſe her before my Face.</hi> Another is, <hi>That</hi> Mr. Okey, <hi>being a Citizen of a mild and ſoft Spirit, was hectored by her Husband to neglect his Truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer. What is alledged concerning the Gentleman in <hi>Grays-Inne</hi> is utterly falſe, I have known him now above twenty years, and never heard any Perſon but my Wife ſay any thing ill of him. He is near eighty years old, ſhe fell upon him and beat him, becauſe he condemned her, I never ſaw or heard him carry himſelf uncivilly towards her by word or deed. This alſo is a Device to take off his Teſtimony. For Mr. <hi>Okey,</hi> if he hath done any wrong in his Truſt, it hath been to me. He hath permitted her both to uſe and abuſe his Name as ſhe and her Counſel pleaſed againſt me, yet ſhe hath abuſed his Wife and Children e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them. Certainly a Woman of greater Falſhood and Ingratitude never lived; her Uſage of that Perſon and Family (who were as a Father and Mother to her in her Troubles) is enough alone to convince any Perſon of what Spirit ſhe is.</p>
            <p>I never moved the Truſtee to do any thing unfair, nor to omit his Duty. I never yet made uſe of any Protection, nor did I ever in the greateſt of my Troubles ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any, but now when my Wife maliciouſly endeavoured to have me arreſted on the Bond of 5000 <hi>l.</hi> ſhe entred into before her Marriage to her firſt Husband; nor did I ever, nor would I offer to inſiſt on any ſuch Shift againſt any other Suit. She knows I voluntarily waved it. As to <hi>Bethel her Confidence,</hi> of whom ſhe will one day be <hi>aſhamed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.13.</note> when that <hi>Calf</hi> cannot ſave her. Sir, You cannot but obſerve the malicious and venemous Compoſition of this Libel. What is left unſaid, that might render me odious? Yet Sir, you ſee there is no Proof nor Reference to any Perſon to juſtify any thing in it. It is only the Wind of my Wives Spleen, who like the wild Aſſe in <hi>Jer.</hi> is ſaid <hi>to ſnuff up the Wind at her pleaſure; and in her Occaſion who can turn her away?</hi> You know how <hi>Occaſion</hi> is rendred in this Place <hi>if ſuch.</hi> When ſhe hath filled up the Meaſure of her Iniquity, God will find her out.</p>
            <p>Sir, I think I have omitted nothing that deſerves to be taken notice of, only this, I have none of her Eſtate in my Hands, I left it ſecure four years ſince, and better by ſeveral hundreds of Pounds than I found it. I am out of Purſe above 600 <hi>l.</hi> for her ſelf, Children, and Suits occaſioned by her, beſides the 700 <hi>l.</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on her Children. You may plainly ſee it is not the Eſtate is the Difference by the ſeveral Awards I have agreed unto; you may as plainly ſee it is a Separation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:15"/> not. And ſince it is ſo, I hope no indifferent Perſon will think it reaſonable, after ſuch unparallel'd Wrongs and Perfidiouſneſs in a Wife, that ſhe ſhall go away a Gainer by me, leave me to pay her Debts, particularly her Debt ſued for by her Confederates in the Duke of <hi>York's</hi> Name, carry away with her my Plate and Jewels I had in my former Wives days to the value of 170 <hi>l.</hi> which I never gave her; ſeventy Pound more ſhe received and kept, which was ſent me by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change from the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and ſeveral other Sums: And ſeveral of my Goods ſhe hath robb'd me of beſides, ſhe hath ſcarce left me any Bed or Table Linnen; ſhe hath ſold my Picture ſet in Gold, which before I married ſhe begg'd of me, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing her Affection with ſuch an Emphaſis, that no Man could have believed counterfeit. I can hardly forbear, but will ſay no more, but that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir, your honouring Servant, <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Scriptures added to the Libel, my Wife knows, I ſent her long ſince with a private Admonition. I now ſend her theſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Amos 5.5.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Seek not</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">That is the Idol wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippped in <hi>Bethel,</hi> which was a Provocation, and Cauſe of Divorce twixt God and his Church.</note> Bethel, — <hi>For</hi> Bethel <hi>ſhall come to naught.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And theſe I ſend, as well to her Friend and his Secretary <hi>Thompſon,</hi> as to her ſelf.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 14.1.</bibl> 
                  <hi>The Fool hath ſaid in his Heart, There is no God.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>(But)</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iſa. 33.1.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Wo to thee that ſpoileſt, and thou waſt not ſpoiled; and dealeſt treacherouſly, and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee. When thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoil, thou ſhalt be ſpoiled; and when thou ſhalt make an end to deal treacherouſly, they ſhall deal treacherouſly with thee.</hi>
               </q>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:15"/>
            <head>The <hi>DEPOSITIONS</hi> of <hi>WITNESSES, proving the Premiſſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THomas Danſon,</hi> Miniſter, depoſeth, That he being deſired by Mr. <hi>Cag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to endeavour a Reconciliation betwixt him and his Wife, did endeavou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to effect the ſame. Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very deſirous of Reconciliation, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in no ſort to ſeparate. That Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was averſe, but before the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rences he hath heard, Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> and her Children ſay, That <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> was careful o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them in their Maintenance and Education, and provided (to uſe her own words nobly for them; but after the Differences Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> complained that her Husban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had waſted her Eſtate, but this Deponent could not find any ſuch thing. Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Wife did abſcond her ſelf from him, but Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> often deſired this Deponen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to intreat her to return home. That this Deponent during this Agitation, at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Requeſt of Mrs. <hi>Cage,</hi> did treat with <hi>Slingsby Bethel</hi> touching the Compoſure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Differences, and did propoſe at Mr. <hi>Cage's</hi> Requeſt, That the Difference<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might be ſtated, and a Trial at Law had upon an Iſſue out of Chancery, for ſpeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> determining of the Differences, or elſe that a Reference might be had to ſome in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>different Perſons touching the ſaid Differences, or to that effect: But ſaith, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid <hi>Slingsby Bethel</hi> was averſe to both the ſaid Propoſals, and ſaid, That ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Propoſitions was a Trick in Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> to put his Wife by, or off the Advantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe had againſt him in Law. And this Deponent hath been informed, that M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bethel</hi> ſpake very hardly of this Deponent upon the Exchange in <hi>London,</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offering ſuch Propoſitions on the behalf of a Perſon that has been ſo ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (as Mr. <hi>Bethel</hi> ſaid) to his Wife. <hi>Note,</hi> (the Baſeneſs was to forbid her his Company<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHarles Cremer</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> Eſquire, depoſeth, That ſome Differences betwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Wife were heretofore referred to this Deponent, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> afterward to this Deponent, and one Mr. <hi>Barrington,</hi> one Mr. <hi>Reynold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and Mr. <hi>Doelittle;</hi> and afterwards to Sir <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> and after to Mr. <hi>Powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> That their Differences aroſe from ſmall Beginnings; that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not averſe to a Reconciliation, and that on ſuch Terms, as this Deponen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and others truſted to arbitrate, ſhould think fit: and remembers Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſubſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed to ſome Propoſals made by this Deponent and Mr. <hi>Barrington,</hi> the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (which Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> inform'd this Deponent) Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> refuſed to agree unto, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Propoſals did relate to the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi>'s Behaviour, and the Eſtate. This Dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nent remembers one Difference that grew at <hi>Highgate</hi> by the broaching of a Barr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Beer by his Order againſt her Mind, whereupon ſhe ſaid ſhe would part, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accordingly deſired this Deponent ſo to act as ſhe might live ſeparate. And this D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ponent did move Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſeveral times to ſeparate, but could not prevail wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, nor did ever Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> move this Deponent for any ſeparate living.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ABraham Barrington</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Gent. depoſeth alſo on Oath, That <hi>Charles Cremer</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> and this Deponent did often meet and endeavour a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>econciliation betwixt Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Wife; and this Deponent at all times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> averſe to a Separation, and would not allow of it to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcours'd of. That the Differences were about very ſmall matters. And as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Eſtate, this Deponent did not find it to be true, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> had waſted the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me. That Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> did acquaint this Deponent, that ſhe lay privately, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d hide her ſelf, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> might not find her, declaring that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould compell her to live with him; but Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did often urge this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent to deſire his Wife to return to live with him. That this Deponent never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und by diſcourſing with themſelves, or their Acquaintance, that there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny Cauſe by any of the Differences conſiderable enough to occaſion them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve ſeparate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Ohn Okey</hi> depoſeth, That Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> often declared before the Differences, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was put to great Troubles and Charges in Suits for her and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Daughter <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and yet greatly commended him for his Love and Kindneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SArah Okey</hi> ſwears the ſame, and that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> in the time of the Marriage-Treaty declared her Daughters ſhould have but little, at another time 400 <hi>l.</hi> piece, and ſhe would not ſtraiten her own Condition. That Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Houſe at <hi>Highgate,</hi> and ſeveral Servants for the maintenance and education of his Wife and Children, and educated the Children very well in Muſick, Dancing, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther Accompliſhments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Ohn Okey</hi> ſwears to the latter part, and that before the Differences Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly managed the Eſtate, and ſecured to the ſaid Daughters 700 <hi>l.</hi> by good City-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecurity; 400 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>Mary Okey</hi> at the Day of Marriage, and 16 <hi>l. per annum</hi> for loaths in the mean time; and upon <hi>Elizabeth Blackwel</hi> 300 <hi>l.</hi> and 12 <hi>l. per annm.</hi> Which 16 <hi>l.</hi> and 12 <hi>l.</hi> they both received duly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Securities were taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Childrens Names, and delivered to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANthony Smith,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſetled 100 <hi>l.</hi> more on <hi>Elizabeth Blackwel</hi> by a Statute from Mr. <hi>Garthe.</hi> And that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> bought and ſued for the Houſe in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hancery-Lane,</hi> to be ſetled in Truſt for his Wife; and that the Deponent engroſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Deed of Aſſignment to Mr. <hi>Okey,</hi> and delivered it to him with a Declaration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gned and ſealed by Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> that the Mony was his Wives, and the Houſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eyed to <hi>Okey</hi> on Truſt for her, and at her Diſpoſe without her Husband; yet note, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaith, <hi>her Husband would have taken it to himſelf;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> and his Wife, and many other Perſons know, That Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age</hi> was reſolved before this barbarous Uſage, to make each of the Daughters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orth a thouſand Pound; they know alſo how he reſolved to do it; and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo he reſolved before this Difference to ſecure 200 <hi>l. per annum</hi> for his Wife, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng her Life; they alſo know how and which way he intended to do that, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould have done it, although no way obliged to it. But pray obſerve how ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="depositions">
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:16"/>
            <head>All the Depoſitions following were taken at the Requeſt of Mr. <hi>Barrington,</hi> and other the Arbitrators, for their ſatisfaction, by the Conſent and Agreemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of my ſelf and Wife, except Mrs. <hi>Langly,</hi> who was ſworn by the order o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sir <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> Sollicitor General.</head>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>MAry Husband,</hi> Wife of <hi>Thomas Husband</hi> of St. <hi>Andrew Holborn,</hi> Gent. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Oath, That ſhe this Deponent lived with Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> at the time that ſhe married Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> about a year and half before the ſaid Marriage, and about a year and half after; and ſaith, That during the time ſhe lived with Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> after the ſaid Marriage, and they kept Houſe, ſhe this Deponent did keep (by Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi>'s order) and lay out the Mony for the Houſhhold Expences, which ſhe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and gave her an Account how the ſame was expended. And this Deponent ſaith, That ſhe doth not know or ever heard, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did ever require any Accompt of Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> of the Mony received for the ſaid Family-Expences. Nor did this Deponent know, or ever hear, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did complain, or ſay at any time, that there was too much Proviſions or Mony ſpent in the Family by Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> or her Children. And this Deponent ſaith, that during this Deponents li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Family, there was always Plenty of Proviſions of all ſorts convenient, and of Mony; and this Deponent hath received ſeveral conſiderable Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for that purpoſe, as ſometimes Ten Pounds, ſometimes Twenty Pounds, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, ſometimes leſs, And when Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent to M. <hi>Cage</hi> for more, it was ſent; and this Deponent laid out what ſhe received for that purpoſe, as Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> thought fit. And this Deponent ſaith, That during that time the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very loving and kind to Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> and her Children, which ſhe hath ſince often acknowledged. And this Deponent ſaith as to the Quarrels and Diſcontents between them, the firſt that this Deponent took notice of was at <hi>Wooborn,</hi> upon ſome paſſages and provoking words Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> took very unkindly of her. And this Deponent remembers there was a great Quarrel upon Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi>'s ſaying Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> killed his former Wife, which Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> told Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſhe heard from this Deponent, and that this Deponent heard it from one Mrs. <hi>Greenhil.</hi> And Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> deſired this Deponent to put it upon that Mrs. <hi>Greenhil,</hi> and deſired this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent to make Oath that Mrs. <hi>Greenhil</hi> ſpake thoſe words, which this Deponent refuſed to do; for indeed this Deponent never heard any other Perſon but Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> her ſelf ſpeak thoſe words, or any other to that effect. And ſeveral other Quarrels have been upon the like Provocations. But this Deponent doth not know or believe, or ever heard, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did uſe any Violence, Force, or Hurt to her Perſon, or deny her or her Children any thing ſhe deſired for her ſelf or them. But knows that <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> deſired ſeveral times, that both ſhe and her Children would wear and have better Cloaths and things than they had or did wear, but ſhe would not. And this Deponent hath heard Mrs <hi>Cage's</hi> Daughter, Miſs <hi>Okey,</hi> ſeveral times complain, that her Mother and Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> had Quarrels about her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beating her the ſaid Miſs <hi>Okey;</hi> and this Deponent knows ſhe was always very ſevere to her ſaid Daughter. And this Deponent doth not know, or ever heard by any of the Servan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Children in the Houſe that Mr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:17"/> but very ſmall Trifles. And this Deponent hath ſeveral times been informed by Mrs. <hi>Blackwel</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cage's</hi> Daughter, and Mrs. <hi>Roſe</hi> her Neece, that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> led Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> a very weary Life by picking Quarrels with him, and vexed him with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roſs Expreſſions. And this Deponent hath heard Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſeveral times confeſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he and her Children were as happy in her marrying Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> as any Perſon could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and verily believes ſhe and they might be happy ſtill, in caſe ſhe would forbear her ill Words and Carriages towards him. Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very careful of her in her Sickneſs, and when he conceived ſhe was in a Conſumption, bought her a Cup of Maſſy Gold to drink new Milk and Sugar of Roſes in, and many times hath put in ſeveral Pieces of Gold to boil in Broth made for her, and many other Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of great Affection he hath ſhewed to her and her Children.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mary Husband.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat. <date>9<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Die <hi>Martii,</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Wm. Beverſham,</hi> Per <hi>S. Poynter.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="depositions">
               <p>
                  <hi>RObert Loveday,</hi> Servant to Sir <hi>Purbeck Temple,</hi> maketh Oath, That he lived with Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his now Wife, as their Servant, above two years, and knows, that during all this time Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> kept a very plentiful Houſe for their Family, and never heard but that they did ſo after this Deponent came away. And this Deponent and the other Servants obſerved, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very careful that his Wife ſhould not want Mony or Proviſions for the Family, and knows Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> paid the Butcher, Brewer, Baker, and Mealman, very well, and never heard any of them complain, or ſay they were ill paid, or ſtayed at all for their Mony. Nor did this Deponent ever hear Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> complain, or ſay that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſpent too much Mony or Proviſions in the Family, or for her Children. But this Deponent always carried home what Mony Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent for, and Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> hath ſent home to his Wife, when he was not there, what Rarities were in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, either Fiſh or Fowl. And this Deponent hath often deſired the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> from her Husband, that ſhe would ſend for what ſhe had a mind to. And this Deponent ſaith, that he and the other Servants have obſerved many Quarrels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Wife about her beating her Children, and knows that the Children were glad when Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> came home to make their Mother and them Friends. And this Deponent and other Servants have obſerved, That Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> would be very croſs, and give her Husband very ill Words, inſomuch that he hath ſeveral times riſen from his Dinner and Supper, and gone into the Garden, to avoid being provoked by her, and ſometimes roſe in the Night, and walked the moſt part of the Night in the Gallery and Garden, and in the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing came away to <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> in diſcontent. And this Deponent and the other Servants have often wondred why ſhe was ſo unkind to her Husband, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied him for the unquiet Life ſhe led him, when he was ſo kind to her and her Children. And this Deponent doth not know, or ever heard, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was the firſt Occaſion or Beginning of any of the Quarrels: but hath often heard the Children and other Servants ſay, that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was the Occaſion thereof, and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> about very ſmall matters. And this Deponent remembers that one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:17"/> were at Mr. <hi>Cage</hi>'s Houſe at Supper, Mr. <hi>Creamer</hi> asked for ſome ſtrong Beer, and Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> bid this Deponent go broach a Barrel: But Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> at Table ſpake ſome croſs words about it, contradicting the ſame, (but the very words this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent cannot remember.) But Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> taking them ill, ſhewed ſome diſcontent, whereupon Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> openly at the Table, ſaid, <hi>She cared not for his ugly looks;</hi> which cauſed a very great diſcontent in Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> ſo that he left the Table, and Friends, and went away. But the Deponent never knew or heard that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did any ways offer any wrong, violence, or hurt to her Perſon, or her Children, although many times ſhe would make him very angry. And this Deponent hath often heard the other Servants ſay, that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> might live happily and well with Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> if ſhe her ſelf pleaſed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Robert Loveday.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat <date>13 Die <hi>Martii</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Will. Beverſham.</hi> Per. <hi>S. Poynter.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>LEttice Dickman,</hi> Wife of <hi>William Dickman</hi> of <hi>Wapping,</hi> Confectioner, maketh oath, that ſhe lived with Madam <hi>Cage</hi> as her Servant at <hi>Highgate,</hi> and waited upon her and her Children about one Year, ending between <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide</hi> laſt. And hath many times obſerved Madam <hi>Cage</hi> and her Husband very kind one to the other, and ſome other times at great Differences and Diſcontents one with the other: But doth not know that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ever uſed any force, violence, or wrong to her Perſon, but hath heard very angry, paſſionate words and expreſſions paſs between them: But this Deponent knows, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very loving and kind to the Children, and ſeveral Quarrels were about her beating of them, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Mrs. <hi>Okey,</hi> to whom ſhe was very ſevere. And knows, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did ſeveral times deſire, and offer, that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> and her Children would have more, and better Clothes, and things than they had, which ſhe would not; and yet neither of them wanted any thing fitting. And this Deponent remembers, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> by reaſon of angry words between them, hath roſe from the Table ſeveral times, and out of his Bed, and walked diſcontentedly in the Garden, and Gallery, moſt part of the night, and believes that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was extream paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and provoking to her Husband, upon ſmall occaſions. And this Deponent remembers particularly a Difference between them, occaſioned by her beating Mrs. <hi>Blackwel,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> chiding her for, ſhe took her Bed; and Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> came ſeveral times to her Bed-ſide, and asked her how ſhe did, to whom ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>As well as a Woman that had ſo bad a Husband as ſhe had, could do.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> deſired to know in what he was ſo bad; She replied, <hi>He killed his former Wife, and would now kill her.</hi> And this Deponent verily believes, that they might have lived as happily as any Perſons, if Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> would have moderated her paſſionate expreſſions, which were indeed very abuſive: And this Deponent ſeveral times told Madam <hi>Cage</hi> as much. And this Deponent believes Madam <hi>Cage</hi> is ſatisfied ſo much; for this Deponent being ſince married, ſhe met Madam <hi>Cage</hi> in the Street, and ſhe gave this Deponent good advice touching this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents Carriage towards her Husband; and adviſed the Deponent to avoid what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:18"/> was deſirous to have the Children well educated. And a Muſick-maſter came from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Highgate</hi> frequently to teach them. And this Deponent remembers, that in a Quarrel at Mr. <hi>Cage</hi>'s Chamber at <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was ſo provoked by her purſuing him with provoking expreſſions, out of one Room into another, that finding a Knife at his Clerks Desk, he ſnatch'd it up, tore open his Doublet; and if this Deponent had not got hold of his, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi>'s Hand, verily believes his Diſcontent and Rage was ſo great, he had ſtabbed himſelf, which this Deponent (by the Providence of God) prevented.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Lettice Dickman.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat <date>19<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Die <hi>Martii</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Will. Beverſham.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>WHereas the ſaid Madam</hi> Cage <hi>hath informed Mr.</hi> Sol. General, <hi>That at</hi> Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontide <hi>laſt, the ſaid Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>forced her to viſit the Marqueſs of</hi> Dorcheſters <hi>Lady, and in the mean time Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>and Mrs.</hi> Ap-Rice <hi>were above in her Chamber alone; and when Mrs.</hi> Cage <hi>came, ſhe found her Chamber diſordered, and her Bed tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; and that ſhe chiding her Maid</hi> Mary <hi>for not ſetting her Chamber in order, her ſaid Maid replied, that Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>and Mrs.</hi> Ap-Rice <hi>were there all the Afternoon, and ſhe durſt not come into the ſaid Chamber.</hi> Now</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Langly</hi> Gentlewoman maketh oath, That ſhe this Deponent, was Servant to the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> from three Weeks after <hi>Eaſter</hi> laſt was twelve Month, till about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> laſt paſt, and knows all the ſaid Information (if any ſuch were) to be untrue; for Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> had appointed that viſit ſeveral days before Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> came home, and knows Madam <hi>Cage</hi> made but one viſit to the Marchioneſs all the time Mrs. <hi>Ap-Rice</hi> was there, and never made any other viſit at any time when Mrs. <hi>Ap-Rice</hi> was at <hi>Highgate;</hi> and knows, that during all the time Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was at the Marchioneſs, Mrs. <hi>Ap-Rice</hi> and her Husband were in the Orchard with the Children and this Deponent, and did not go out of the Orchard till Madam <hi>Cage</hi> returned home; nor was the Bed or Chamber any way diſordered, nor did this Deponent ever know, believe, or ſay, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Ap-Rice</hi> were ever together alone in any Room or Chamber. And this Deponent ſaith, that no Maid called <hi>Mary</hi> (but this Deponent) lived with Madam <hi>Cage</hi> all laſt Summer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as to the Quarrels between them, this Deponent ſaith, they were occaſioned by Mrs. <hi>Cages</hi> abuſive Language to her Husband, when he hath chid her for beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Children, which ſhe did very frequently, and unreaſonably; inſomuch, that the Children have oftentimes threatned to run away, and declared they would marry, one a Tinker, and another a Cobler, rather than endure <hi>their Mothers cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> And this Deponent knoweth Madam <hi>Cage</hi> hath ſpoken very maliciouſly and unhandſomly of her ſaid Husband, ſometimes ſaying of him, he is an <hi>ugly fat Bear,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>ugly Dog,</hi> and ſometimes ſaid ſhe received a Letter from the <hi>ugly Dog</hi> when ſhe received a Letter from Mr. <hi>Cage.</hi> And this Deponent knows, that Madam <hi>Cage</hi> and her Daughter <hi>Blackwel</hi> agreed together not to come to <hi>London</hi> and live with Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> and one time Madam <hi>Cage</hi> did reſolve to remove the Goods from <hi>Highgate</hi> into the Country, and take a Houſe and live by her ſelf; and ſaid, when Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> came into the Country ſhe would fly to her Brother <hi>Roſe,</hi> for Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> would be afraid to go thither. And this Deponent knows that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:38311:18"/> of) the Children and her Siſter many times importun'd her to be reconciled to her Husband, and told her how kindly he ſpake of her; but ſhe refuſed and would never hearken to it, but would part from him: And when ſhe had wrote a provoking Letter to Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> the Children and her Siſter importun'd her to write a kind concluſion of that Letter, and ſet her name to it, which ſhe would not; and yet Mrs. <hi>Blackwel</hi> ſent in her Mothers name for Money, by the ſame Meſſenger, and Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent it. And this Deponent knows, that when Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> hath grieved and diſcontented Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> with her ill Language and Carriage, and ſhe hath been informed of his diſcontent, ſhe hath been very merry and pleaſant, and no way concerned at it, as this Deponent could perceive. And this Deponent hath heard Madam <hi>Cage</hi> oftentimes acknowledge, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very kind to her and her Children, and that their own Fathers could not have been more kind to them; and being deſired to go to <hi>London</hi> after the firſt difference, to ſubmit her ſelf, ſhe ſaid ſhe would not go after him, and all the World ſhould never make her ſubmit, calling her ſaid Husband <hi>fat Bear,</hi> and <hi>ugly Dog:</hi> And this Deponent did never know or hear, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did ever offer any wrong, violence, or hurt to her, or that he ſuffered her to want any thing ſhe deſired, but believes, and hath heard from the Children and Servants, that ſhe might live plentifully, happily, and well if ſhe pleaſed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mary Langly.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat. <date>5<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Die <hi>Maii</hi> 1675,</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me, <hi>Tho. Eſtcourt.</hi> Per. <hi>S. Poynter.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>MAry Ap-Rice</hi> Wife of <hi>Benedict Ap-Rice</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>Giles</hi> in the Fields, in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> Gentlewoman, maketh Oath, That ſhe came to live with Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> his Lady on the <hi>Friday</hi> in <hi>Eaſter</hi>-week laſt was two Years, and continued in her Service till near <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> following, and during that time this Deponent knoweth, that by agreement with Mr. <hi>Roſe</hi> a Butcher, he was to ſerve the Family with Beef, Mutton, Veal, Pork, Tongues, and Udders, and alſo Lamb, at a certain price; and he did ſerve the Family with what Meat was beſpoke by Madam <hi>Cage</hi> her order from time to time; and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> paid him for the ſame when he required it, or in ſome very little time after. And alſo the <hi>Meal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <hi>Brewer.</hi> And this Deponent ſaith, ſhe never heard that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did find fault with his Lady for ſpending too much, either Proviſions or Money; but when the Money that was in the Houſe was near ſpent (as there were ſeveral occaſions of buying Poultry at the Door) when Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent for more Money, it was ſent to her, or brought home by Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> the next time he came. And this Deponent ſaith, that there was not any want or ſhortneſs in Proviſions or Money for the Family at any time, whilſt this Deponent lived there; for this Deponent did keep the Money for the Family-Expences by Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi>'s orders, and gave her from time to time an account thereof; and this Deponent doth not know, or ever heard that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did ever deny any thing, or Money for Clothes, or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for Mrs <hi>Cage</hi>'s Daughters; but knows, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> would have had both Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> her ſelf, and Children, have had more Clothes, and better than they had which Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſeveral times refuſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:19"/>
               <p>And as to the Quarrels and Diſcontents between Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his ſaid Lady, whilſt ſhe lived there, They were occaſioned about ſmall trifling things, which grew into words, but doth not know, or ever heard that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ever uſed any force, violence, or wrong to Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi>'s Perſon, but hath often heard from her Daughters and Neeces, that their Mother and Aunt was the firſt occaſion and beginning of ſuch Differences and Quarrels. And this Deponent hath often heard Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> and her Daughters acknowledge Mr. <hi>Cage</hi>'s love and kindneſs to them, and Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> in particular, ſaying, Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was as good a Husband as any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had. And this Deponent ſaith, that when Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> came home to <hi>Highgate,</hi> (which was commonly on <hi>Saturdays,</hi>) he ſpent moſt of his time in Mrs. <hi>Cages</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and believes he delighted ſo to do; for this Deponent never knew him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company other Perſons to any the Alehouſes or Taverns there. And (excepting when ſuch Quarrels were) this Deponent hath heard and ſeen Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Lady both of them, as kind and affectionate to each other as any Perſons (as this Deponent believes) could be. And this Deponent knoweth, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent many extraordinary proviſions from <hi>London</hi> home, and the Houſe was very ſeldom (if at all) without ſtrong Beer, and Ale, and Wine, which Mrs. <hi>Blackwel</hi> kept the Keys of. And this Deponent ſaith, that when Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> was ill, this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent uſing her utmoſt care about the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Cage,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof, he gave this Deponent twenty Shillings, and deſired this Deponent to continue her care to, and be very careful of the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> and this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent never received of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> any Gift in Money, Proviſions, or other things whatſoever. And this Deponent ſaith, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was never to this (Deponents knowledge) at any Lodging of this Deponents.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mary Ap-Rice.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat. <date>24 Die <hi>Februarii</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Will. Beverſham.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>MArgaret Fyney</hi> maketh oath, That in the Year 1672 this Deponent came to ſerve Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Wife at <hi>Highgate</hi> as Cook-maid, and lived that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmer there with them. And ſaith, that ſhe hath lived ſeveral Years in ſeveral Families, of Perſons of Quality, and never did ſee more plenty for their own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, than was in Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi>'s Family, and never knew that there was any want of Money or Proviſions; and when there was any thing that was rare, and in ſeaſon, it was ſent home by Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> to his Wife. And this Deponent ſaith, that all the Servants obſerved, that whatſoever Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent for, either Money, or other things, Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent it: And this Deponent carried Money and other things home ſeveral times to Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> from her Husband, which ſhe ſent for. And this Deponent knows, that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was very loving and kind to the Children, and whatever they deſired for Clothes, or other things, Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> bought and ſent them home, and never knew or heard that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> did beat or diſcontent the Children: But knows, that many times Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> would quarrel needleſsly at Dinner with Mr. <hi>Cage,</hi> and that he hath left his Dinner and gone out into the Garden, and ſate there; and ſometimes out of the Bed, and walked about moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the Servants many times pitied Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> for the unquiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:19"/> times, and turned her out of her ſight, and ſhe durſt not come into her ſight until Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> came home, who uſually reconciled them; and knows, that the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren always rejoiced when Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> was to come home; and believes, that Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> did live as freely, and happily, as any Perſon need do, and might ſtill have ſo done, if it were not her own fault; for the Servants obſerved ſhe would provoke him with very ill words, upon very ſmall for no occaſion.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Margaret Fyney.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat. <date>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Die <hi>Martii</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Will. Beverſham.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>MAry Bucknal</hi> maketh oath, That ſhe lived about one Year, but ſomething leſs with Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> and his Lady, as Cook-maid; and knows that they kept a plentiful Houſe for their Family, and that Mr. <hi>Cage</hi> (during this Deponents living there) always ſent home what Proviſions or Money Mrs. <hi>Cage</hi> ſent for, and doth not believe, or ever heard, that he ever denied any Money, or other thing for his Wife or Children, but knows, they might have had more and better Clothes than they had, if ſhe had pleaſed. And hath heard Madam <hi>Cage</hi> many times acknowledge, and ſay, that ſhe was as happy in a Husband, and her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in a Father, as ſhe could deſire; but there were ſeveral Quarrels between <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> and his Lady, ſometimes about her beating her Children, and turning <hi>Mrs. Okey</hi> out of her ſight; and ſometimes about ſome croſs and unkind ſlighting Words or Expreſſions ſhe would give her ſaid Husband; and ſometimes about her forbidding what he had ordered to be done: And ſaith, that all the Servants took notice how ſhe would ſlight and croſs him; and many times pitied him for the diſcontented life ſhe led him; and hath heard her Daughters ſeveral times ſay, that they wondred their Mother would be ſo croſs unto, and quarrel with their Father; and would always ſay, that their Mother began the Quarrels. And this Deponent knoweth, that <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> hath been ſo provoked by her ill Language, that he hath ſeveral times aroſe from the Table at Dinners and Suppers in Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; and many times out of his Bed, and walked many parts of the night diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented in the Houſe and Garden alone. And this Deponent remembers, that <hi>Mr. Creamer</hi> and his Lady coming to <hi>Mr. Cage</hi>'s Houſe at <hi>Highgate, Mrs. Cage</hi> was diſpleaſed, and would ſtay in the Kitchin; and <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> intreated her very much to walk into the Parlour and keep them Company, which ſhe at length did: But at Supper <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> ordered a Barrel of <hi>March</hi> Beer to be broached, which <hi>Mrs. Cage</hi> was angry at, and gave <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> ſome ill words openly at Table, (as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then preſent diſcourſed in the Kitchin:) And <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> looking angrily upon her, ſhe then ſaid, <hi>She cared not for his ugly looks;</hi> which cauſed great diſconten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> between them. And <hi>Mrs. Aſh</hi> told this Deponent, <hi>Mrs. Cage</hi> was with Child and miſcarried then, and that ſhe might have prevented it if ſhe would. But this Deponent doth not know or ever heard that <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> was ever ſo provoked to ſtrike or hurt her, but the Servants have often ſaid, they wondred at their Maſters patience, that he would bear ſuch uſage. And this Deponent ſaith, that <hi>Mr. Cag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did always expreſs great kindneſs to <hi>Mrs. Cage,</hi> in ſending home what Proviſion were in ſeaſon, (though he was not there) and Wine and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:20"/> there was no want or ſcarcity of Proviſions, or Money in the Family: And <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> took care that the Family, Children, and Servants, ſhould be inſtructed in the fear of God; for he uſually (if not every Sunday) had ſome Miniſter preached twice in the Family, uſually <hi>Mr. Reynolds, Mr. Danſon,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Danſon,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Fowler.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Mary Bucknal.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat <date>16 Die <hi>Martii</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Will. Beverſham.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>
                  <hi>SImon Picknol</hi> Servant to <hi>Tobias Cage</hi> Eſquire, maketh oath, That he came the fourth of <hi>May</hi> laſt to ſerve the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> at his Houſe at <hi>Highgate,</hi> and hath lived with him as a Servant to this day. And this Deponent ſaith, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this great difference hapned between the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> and his Lady, this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent bought in moſt of the Proviſions for the Houſe at <hi>Highgate,</hi> and ſeveral times received Money of the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> to buy the ſame. And this Deponent ſaith, that until the difference hapned, this Deponent did neither know nor hear that the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> did ſuffer any want of Proviſions or Money in the Family, or that the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> ever found fault that they ſpent too much. And this Deponent ſaith, that ſince the ſaid difference, the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> often enquired whether they wanted either Meat or Money at <hi>Highgate.</hi> And this Deponent did acquaint the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage's</hi> Wife had forbid him (this Deponent) to receive or bring any Money from him; after which time, this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent did not receive any Money for the ſaid Houſe, or Proviſions from the ſaid <hi>Mr. Cage,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Mrs. Cage</hi> having forbid this Deponent to receive any. And this Deponent ſaith, that the ſaid <hi>Mrs. Cage</hi> ſeveral times ſent this Deponent to Town about her Buſineſs, and forbad him (this Deponent) to come at <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> her Husband.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Simon Picknol.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat <date>24 Die <hi>Februarii</hi> 1674.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Tho. Eſtcourt.</hi> Per <hi>S. Poynter.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <p>WHereas this Deponent <hi>Robert Fairbeard</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> Eſquire, is informed, that the Defendatns Wife did affirm to her Counſel at the <hi>Rolls,</hi> the laſt day of the laſt Term, that her Husband would not allow her maintenance for her ſelf and Servant; This Deponent maketh oath that he hath known both the Defendants ever ſince they were married, and before, and hath been often in the Family; but this Deponent never underſtood that the Defendant the Husband denied any thing neceſſary or convenient for his Wife. And this Deponent being their Kinſman, was deſired to prevail with the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant the Wife, to remove out of <hi>Mr. Cage</hi>'s Chamber in <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the laſt Term, that he might have his Chamber quiet for his Buſineſs. And in the Deponents preſence, <hi>Mr. Cage</hi> offered his ſaid Wife, that if ſhe would diet any where near <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> until after Term, he would pay twenty Shillings per Week for her ſelf and Maid; and then offered her five Guinies, twenty Shillings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:20"/> Pieces of Gold, and would have delivered them unto her, to pay for ſuch diet for her Maid and ſelf for five Weeks. But ſhe refuſed to receive any Money of her Husband.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Robert Fairbeard.</signed>
                  <dateline>Jurat <date>13 Die <hi>Februarii</hi> 1676.</date>
                  </dateline> Coram me <hi>Tho. Eſtcourt.</hi> Per <hi>S. Poynter.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>Many other Depoſitions I omit.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce my Wife had notice this Anſwer was Pen'd; ſhe, her Friend, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, reſolved to improve the Slander of the Baſtard, to juſtifie her eighteen Months ſeparation, before that pretence had any Being; and the better to colour it, have by ſurpriſe drawn in the aid of Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> You may remember, the Libel pretends, I had a familiar converſe nine Months with a Wench, and lodged her in <hi>Fullers</hi> Rents, to ly in for Neighbourhood. <hi>Note,</hi> She knew this Wench ſhe cauſed her Siſter to hire for me, was a Comrade of a Woman that went by the name of <hi>Mrs. Hilton,</hi> as a Merchant's Widow, but is really the Wife of a Butcher in <hi>Puckridge</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> and ran away from her Husband too, and who (as is now found out) plyed at a Bawdyhouſe near <hi>Bond-Stables,</hi> and hath had a Baſtard, for whoſe cure of the <hi>Pox,</hi> there is now a Suit depending, and Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> is Counſel for the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and <hi>Mr. Ray</hi> is Attorny. This <hi>Hilton</hi> was my Wifes chief Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this Baſtard plot, and whilſt this Wench lived with me, ſhe often lay out with this <hi>Hilton,</hi> and was no doubt imployed as well as her ſelf: You ſee that in <hi>March,</hi> upon <hi>Mr. Creamer</hi>'s ſuſpition, I gave this Wench warning, that for four Months after this ſuſpition of <hi>Mr. Creamers,</hi> and until this Wench was gone, I procured my Couſin <hi>Will. Cage</hi> to live and lodge with me: She had the Baſtard in <hi>January,</hi> ſeven Months after ſhe went from me. I mentioned my Wifes tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with her whilſt ſhe lived with me. Her Daughter <hi>Betty Blackwels</hi> Prediction by Letter to <hi>Mr. Smith.</hi> You have heard of my Wifes frequent and kind viſits to the Wench; whereas a Genleman I ſent to examine the Wench, could never be admitted. And note Sir, that ſhe concealed her being with Child, and went about to murder it in the Houſe of Office, as <hi>Mr. Waingford,</hi> Maſter of the Houſe, and his Wife can teſtifie; either of which (in all likelihood) ſhe ſhould have no reaſon attempt, if I were concerned in it. That I left ten Shillings with Mr. <hi>Waingford</hi> Maſter of the Houſe for Charges to watch and apprehend her. And that I ſue one of my Wifes Confederates in the Spiritual Court for Slander, that the matter may there be enquired into. And Sir, this is obſervable, that after my Wife heard Mr. <hi>Creamer</hi> adviſed to the turning the Maid away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:21"/> Wife again accuſes me, that I had ſent the Wench away to ly in: Hereupon, by Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi>'s advice, I ſent for the Wench, ſtayed her from Service, and gave five Shillings a Week for five Weeks after ſhe was gone from me, that ſhe might appear, and the contrary be obſerved; and after this Slander proved ineffectual, <hi>Betty Blackwels</hi> Letter was ſent.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, ſince my Wife was aſſured I would anſwer her Libel, ſhe and her Friend rage like Satan, foreſeeing the time is ſhort, and in purſuance of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Practice of Subornation and Falſhood, hath ſuborned this Whore. She upon pretence of a Warrant ſent me word by her Nephew, my Clerk, at ten of the Clock at Night, that ſhe was going with her before Sir <hi>W. T.</hi> a Juſtice of Peace. I confeſs, the Suddenneſs of it, and the Time of the Night, made me ſuſpect ſome Deſign and way-laying, being as yet bound to the Peace, however I ſent my Wife word by her Nephew, that I expected ſhe would now ſecure and proſecute the Wench; but miſtruſting ſhe ſhould not, I deſired two Gentlemen of our Houſe to ſtep to the Juſtice to get her ſecured; they attended, and obſerved that the Juſtice gave the Whore that had the Baſtard her Oath, and examin'd her. Certainly this Juſtice of Peace, though a very worthy Perſon, was ſtrangely influenced by her Libel and Friend, to aſſume a Power as a ſingle Juſtice of Peace to examine a Whore <hi>on her Oath</hi> on the Complaint of a Wife againſt her Husband. Indeed if the Baſtard were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, two Juſtices of the Peace, in order to diſcharge the Pariſh, may examine the Matter, but in no other Caſe, elſe the Malice of a Wife by the Teſtimony of a common Whore might defame her Husband. But Sir, the Wench being fore-inſtructed, prompted on and ſurrounded by my Wife and her other Confederaies that Night, fware, that ſhe having lived with me near a year, it was half a year before I had any Commerce with her of that ſort, and that was only four times (as ſhe ſaith); but my Wife was over-heard putting her in mind, that ſhe ſhould ſware I had to do with her nine Months. <hi>Note,</hi> this was to make good her Libel: but obſerve, that when this Mrs. <hi>Hilton</hi> the Agent firſt charged me with the Baſtard, ſhe told to Mr. <hi>Fincham</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fairebeard</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inne,</hi> that the Wench af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed I never had the knowledge of her but once. And now when one of the Gentlemen prayed the Juſtice take notice ſhe was in two Tales, he favourably termed that but Forgetfulneſs; whereas all other Judges allow ſelf-contradicting to be a clear Evidence of Falſhood and Forgery. And mark this, <hi>Sir,</hi> that when the Perſons I ſent earneſtly moved that the Wench ſhould be had to Priſon until I were heard next day, and that it was for my Wife's Credit, if ſhe would avoid all ſuſpicion of having ſuborned this Wench; yet my Wife and her Conſorts oppoſed it; but the Juſtice took a Strangers bare word for her to appear next Day at eleven a Clock, but they never appeared more. For indeed there was no farther Deſign but to have the Whore deliver this Slonder on her Oath, and ſo be gone. And the Juſtice of Peace is now to be examined on all Occaſions as a Witneſs, as to teſtify what the Whore delivered on Oath, which they vainly think will be a ſtabbing Evidence, that any Man though never ſo innocent had a Baſtard; but I doubt not e're long to diſcover more of the Matter without Bribery or Subornation. Sir, this Woman, <hi>Hilton,</hi> was the Perſon that managed this Plot for my Wife from the beginning and that came to me when the Wench (as was pretended) lay in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:21"/> grace. Mark the Deſign: when ſhe ſaw I would not be wrought upon to betray my own Innocency that way, ſhe applied her ſelf to Mr. <hi>Fincham,</hi> offered him, if I would give her ten Pounds, ſhe would bring a Perſon ſhould take off the Child, and give Security from future Charge: but my Innocency was ſuch; I rather choſe to abide a Trial at Law than give one Penny. And I never heard of it more until my Wife ſuborned this Wench to ſwear this, to juſtify her ſelf; nor could I ever light of this Wench or the ſaid <hi>Hilton</hi> ſince the Baſtard pretence, nor can I yet catch this Whore although I do endeavour it; but by the Grace of God as ſoon as poſſibly I can get her Appearance, I will try the matter by a Jury upon an Action of Slander, whether that Baſtard ought to be charged on me, or no: which Action, as the Caſe is, and the Dammages may be laid, I think will lie. And in order to the ſpeedy doing of it, I ſhall take it kindly of my Wife, if ſhe will procure this Wench to give me an Appearance by an Attourney in the Common-Pleas, without further Trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Something may be expected I ſhould ſay as to the Deed printed at large, with deſign either to inſinuate ſome Indiſcretion in giving ſuch a Power, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice in not keeping it according to the Letter. Therefore Sir, I entreat you to conſider that Deed with the Circumſtances ſhe and her Eſtate were in, and you will not (I think) conceive me guilty of much Folly, or any Fraud at all in the penning of it. The Eſtate was but 1500 <hi>l.</hi> ſhe had two Children, and no Debts or Troubles, as ſhe and her Truſtee affirmed. The Eſtate was forfeited, and all liable to be taken away by his Royal Highneſs, except ſuch Part as could be proved granted to her. Now Sir, though her Affection to me before I married her, was by her Subtilty ſet out in as taking Colours as the greateſt Hypocriſy could paint it; her Carriage ſuch, as might have prevailed with a wiſer Man to put Confidence in her who was to be a Wife, eſpecially conſidering the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſhe made of Religion. Yet I endeavoured to ſecure my ſelf, as well againſt her Childrens future Clamours and uncertain Expectations, as from all Suites to diſcover or accompt for her Husband <hi>Okeys</hi> Eſtate, toward which any Lawyer will allow me the pleading this Deed would have gone very far. Sir, you will find ſhe hath not ſuch a Power as ſhe pretends unto, but only the Power of appointing Proportions, as well for her Childrens Preferment, as her own Maintenance; and that muſt be alſo according to Equity and Juſtice, ſo that ſhe cannot give all to her Children, and leave no Maintenance for her ſelf; and the whole is ſo limited, that ſhe cannot diſpoſe of any part of the Principal, but for the Preferment of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhe then had, and might have by me. And if the Truſtee conſents to employ any part of it to any other uſe, he is anſwerable to me for breach of Truſt, and muſt make good the Dammage out of his own Eſtate. And as to the Letter or general Words of the Deed, <hi>viz. [all her Eſtate]:</hi> Was it not a great Fraud in her (and her Truſtee too if he had known it) to conceal and deny her Debts ſhe owed, and ſeveral expenceful Suits ſhe knew I muſt be engaged in, not only to defend the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> made known to me, but to recover that which I never knew of, nor was ever mentioned before I married her? Can it be imagined by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rational Man, that I ſhould intend by that Deed, either that ſhe ſhould give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and I maintain her, and pay her Debts; or that I ſhould ſell my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:22"/> I then knew not of, nor ſhe neither, &amp; that for her &amp; her Children. I could ſay much more, but 'tis not convenient. The Deed is before the L. Chancellor for his Judgment at her Suit. But this I ſay, I never endeavoured to defeat or avoid the true Intent and Meaning of that Deed; but I think now her denying Co-habitation with me hath taken away much of the force of it, and altered the Caſe.</p>
            <p>And as to her Pretences, <hi>That I would have no End, that nothing would ſatisfy me but the whole Eſtate,</hi> you ſee how falſe ſhe is proved. And yet to give a full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and ſtop the Mouth even of Falſhood it ſelf, I make her theſe Offers.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Let her produce any Woman in</hi> England <hi>(except the Whore of her own making) that will ſoberly affirm, that ever I tempted her to any laſcivious act of Dalliance, or any Gentleman that was ever in my company at any ſuch time, or with any ſuch Perſon, I will releaſe her Eſtate, and all claims to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>If ſhe deſires Reconciliation, and will ſubmit her ſelf, make ſuch acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement and ſatisfaction as any two Divines (I having liberty to except againſt two only, and ſhe the like) ſhall think fit and honourable for me to receive, I will not only as to her Eſtate give her choice of the three Awards already made, but if ſhe refuſes them, I will ſubmit all the matters in difference ſhe pretends unto whatſoever (except the pretended Friend) to any two or three private Gentlemen, or Lawyers, that have not been concerned with either ſide, to their final and abſolute determination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ſhe refuſe all theſe Propoſals, judge you Sir, and all the World, whether ſhe can be other than as <hi>Solomon</hi> denotes, ſuch a Woman <hi>as forſakes her Husband, and the Covenant of her God?</hi> or, whether there ever was ſuch a Diabolical combination againſt the Laws of God, Nature, and Humanity, as is between the pretended Friend and her ſelf?</p>
            <p>Sir, I foreſee an Objection will be by this Woman. <hi>What, ſhall I give up a Perſon that has eſpouſed my Quarrel againſt my Husband, and make an agreement and he not included? I cannot in honour do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis my unhappineſs ſhe is not better acquainted with true Honour: where that is, you always find it imprinted in the Mind with indelible Characters; The Flatteries or Pretences of ſuch a Friend could never have prevailed with her to forget her Covenant, nor any ways to wrong her Husband, unto whom 'tis her duty <hi>to do good, and no evil all his days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no diſhonour to turn from an evil way, 'tis no diſhonour to leave this Seducer to the Law; if he hath done well, the Law will juſtifie him; if not, the World will juſtify her Husband. Which is moſt honourable? to prefer the peace and comfort of her Husband, to which ſhe is bound by a ſacred vow, or that of ſuch a Stranger, whoſe own folly hath rendred him lyable to queſtion? Methinks, the four Years diſtraction and wrong I have ſuffered, may reſolve that Doubt in honour; I am ſure it doth in her own Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Sir, You now ſee who it is that ſeparates, and the Cauſe. The Libel tells you, <hi>That ſhe is ſtill at the ſame Lodging I put her in, and never lay a Night out but with my knowledg, at the Houſe of a Friend of mine.</hi> 'Tis true, I could not but know ſhe lay out all that <hi>Whitſon</hi>-Week, but 'twas againſt my Will. 'Tis now twelve Months ſince, but to this day ſhe will not tell where nor with whom ſhe was, nor do I know. Her continuing her Lodging is like that of keeping in my Chamber three Terms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38311:22"/> a deſign to provoke me with ſuch Language, that nothing could be more intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and at the ſame time ſet one <hi>Sorrel</hi> to eveſdrop me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> What I have ſaid is true, you ſee moſt of it is proved, and it is leſs than ſhe knows I can ſay. If I give you an Account of ſome Intrigues in Coll. <hi>Okeys</hi> abſence, and ſome relating to my ſelf, 'twould chill your Blood to read them. I tell you not all that I can of the Actions of the Friend and his Complices, which are not wrapp'd up in ſuch a Cloud of darkneſs, as they conceive; nor do I mention the various Attempts, Factions, and Threats, to effect my Ruine, nor yet the Faction ſet up in the Society where I live. But Sir, I doubt not I ſhall write again; for this Woman is as incorrigible as that duckt under water for a Scold, yet held up her Hands above the water, and made Horns at her Husband. Sir, however I entreat you ſignify the Contents hereof to ſuch Perſons as you think fit, who certainly muſt conclude upon the whole, that although my Wife doth deſign a Separation, ſuppoſing thereby, and by the general words of the Deed, to carry with her all that conſiderable addition I have made by my labours, and thereby hopes to defraud me of what I have expended alſo; and if ſhe be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed therein, yet that the Friend can never make a recompence for the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable and inexpreſſible wrongs he hath done me, by contriving and fomenting thoſe differences, to the utter deſtruction of all the comforts of my life; and that he was the moſt indiſcreet and uncharitable of Men if innocent; the moſt unjuſt, if otherwiſe, to ſue and ſlander a Husband in a Court of Judicature, for, and on the behalf of a Wife, without firſt diſcourſing the Husband, and trying whether he were faulty or no. Yet Sir,</p>
            <p>This I will offer him alſo, let him make out that I have done any thing either imprudently, or diſhoneſtly, relating to the Eſtate, my Wife or Children, and I will forgive all the wrongs he hath done me, taking the Eſtate as it was, the Suits I had of hers, and the improvement I have made.</p>
            <p>☞ Note, <hi>That when my Wife and this Friend had contrived a Suit againſt me and her ſelf in</hi> Chancery, <hi>in the name of</hi> Martha Wilſon, <hi>ſhe petitioned the Honourable the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls, <hi>that ſhe might make anſwer by ſuch Guardian ſhe ſhould chuſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to make uſe of this Friend for countenance: but the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls <hi>declared he would not appoint any Guardian for a Wife, ſhe ſhould anſwer with her Husband, or anſwer alone. And after my Wife had contrived I ſhould be bound to the Peace, this Friend did frequently accompany my Wife to ſeveral Maſters in</hi> Chancery, <hi>and there thruſt himſelf into Suits wherein he was no way concern'd, meerly to provoke me; ſo that I not daring to truſt my ſelf under ſuch provocations, have been forced to neglect the attendance of my Buſineſs my ſelf, by reaſon whereof, ſuch reports have been made, and in ſuch a manner, as would not have been in caſe I were preſent rightly to inform them, and that to my very great damage. There are two remarkable Paſſages of this nature:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>One, My Wife ſeeing me attending at Sir</hi> Andrew Hackets, <hi>ſends privately for the Friend, who before refuſed, and durſt not give me a meeting till I was bound to the Peace, though he was fairly invited to it; yet now he comes, but I having notice of it, and not daring to truſt my ſelf, went away before he came, and thereupon he falls to accuſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting of me to the Maſter, as falſly and barbarouſly as a lying tongue could utter. See the honour of this Woman who hand in hand with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38311:23"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhering my Wife to my face, whilſt I with my three Friends ſtood bound to the Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>☞ <hi>Another time when I petitioned the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls, <hi>that the cauſe between me and the Truſtee might be ſpeedily ſet down for hearing: the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to hear Counſel on both ſides. This precious Friend and his Sollicitor coming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Counſel, fell upon accuſing of me to him: The Maſter of the</hi> Rolls, <hi>though he knew me not, and no Perſon there for me, was ſenſible of ſome unfairneſs, demanded of him, what he was concerned, was he any Truſtee to the Wife or Children, any ways akin to them? He anſwered no: Then, what reaſon have you to ſue the Husband on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his Wife? To which he replies, 'Tis often done in</hi> Chancery; <hi>and thereupon the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls <hi>declared, that if it were ſometimes, yet he knew no reaſon for it, and he doubted Mr.</hi> Cage <hi>had ſome wrong; but Mr.</hi> Hutchins <hi>my Counſel coming in, they fell upon the Buſineſs, and the Counſel preſs d, that the Cauſe might be ſet down to be heard and affirmed, that Witneſſes were examined, and all matters might be ſettled upon the Truſtee's Bill, according to my Lord Chancellor's order of the</hi> 12th <hi>of</hi> June: <hi>But the Friend oppoſing that, Mr.</hi> Hutchins <hi>on my behalf offered to refer all the matters in difference to the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls <hi>himſelf, as a private Perſon, to be ſettled as he ſhould think fit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Appeal, which the Maſter of the</hi> Rolls <hi>was pleaſed to accept, being betwixt a Gentleman and his Wife: but this religious Fomenter of differences, as before to Mr.</hi> Danſon, <hi>now alſo denied all Propoſals that might tend to the ſettlement and the peace of my Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sir, To that ſeeming reflection in the Libel, as a ſhameful thing, that I oppoſe my own Act and Deed, meaning the general words in the Deed printed. I anſwer once for all, That where a man ſeals a general Releaſe, whereby in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Law a Debt or Duty, that the Releaſor knew not of, is diſcharged; yet 'tis the courſe of Equity to relieve againſt that Releaſe: ſo here I do aver, that I knew not of any other Eſtate, Debts, or Suits, nor was there any communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of any other Eſtate or things, than the 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and therefore conſidering the Prize I have met withal in a Wife, I doubt not to find relief in Equity, for it is an axiom as well of <hi>Civilians</hi> as <hi>Logicians. Verba reſtringenda ſunt ad preſentem materiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>The Places where the Perſons live to whom I have referred you.</head>
               <item>SIr <hi>Francis Winnington,</hi> Sollicitor Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, in the <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>William Steynes</hi> in <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> in <hi>Hackney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Creamer</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Fincham</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Barrington</hi> in <hi>Suffolk-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Okey</hi> in <hi>Cateaton-ſtreet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Dun</hi> in <hi>Spittle-fields.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> lives there alſo.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> at <hi>Bun-hill</hi> Fields.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Doelittle</hi> in <hi>Monkwel</hi>-Street.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thankful Owen</hi> in <hi>Bull and Mouth Street.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Madam <hi>Broughton,</hi> and at Mr. <hi>Parſons,</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Fetter-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Madam <hi>Puliſton,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Parſons,</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Fetter-Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Pledger</hi> at Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> the Miniſter in <hi>Thames-ſtreet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elizabeth Gun</hi> at Mr. <hi>Guns</hi> at <hi>Billingsgate.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38311:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
